[音乐播放]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
科尔顿·奥格登：好的 欢迎来到GD50 第5堂课
COLTON OGDEN: All right, welcome to GD50, Lecture 5.
今天的主题是塞尔达的传说 正如你在屏幕上看到的那样
Today's topic is The Legend of Zelda, as you can see on the screen there.
一款非常标志性的游戏
A very iconic game.
上周 我们制作了《超级马里奥兄弟》 它可以说是最具标志性的视频游戏
Last week we did Super Mario Bros, which is arguably the most iconic video game
史无前例的
of all time.
塞尔达传奇是一个势均力敌的竞争者
Legend of Zelda is a close contender.
即使是现在 就像马里奥一样 他们也在制作非常精彩的比赛
Even now, just like with Mario, they're producing very wonderful games.
我想去年《野性的呼吸》夺走了所有的 我忘了是哪一个
I think last year Breath of the Wild took all the, I forget which
这是一场颁奖典礼 或者说颁奖典礼
ceremony it was, or award sort of show.
但它几乎囊括了所有可能的奖项
But it took like every award possible.
就在去年 最新的塞尔达 野性的呼吸
Just last year, the latest Zelda, the Breath of the Wild.
因此 在这样的背景下谈论塞尔达传奇感觉有点不合时宜
So it feels sort of apropos to talk about Legend of Zelda in that context
也是
as well.
以下是原版《塞尔达传奇》的截图
Here's a screenshot of the original Legend of Zelda.
这是NES的头衔 就像超级马里奥兄弟一样--
It was an NES title, just like Super Mario Bros--
就像它那个时代的大多数游戏一样 以瓷砖为基础
just like most games of its time, tile based.
你可以在某种程度上看到周围是如何一点点地分层的瓷砖
You can sort of see how the surroundings are sort of layered tiles bit by bit.
这个游戏的总体目标是探索这个开放的世界 这
The goal of the game overall was to sort of explore this open world, which
这在这方面还是头一回
is kind of a first of its kind.
您控制了Link 如最下面所示
You controlled Link, shown at the very bottom there.
你有剑 你有炸弹 你有箭
You had a sword, yo had bombs, you had arrows.
你想去找红宝石 你得穿过地牢
You want to go find rubies, you went through dungeons.
你杀死了怪物和头目 然后最终的目标
You slayed monsters and bosses, and then ultimately the goal
是为了获得左上角和右上角所示的三重力
was to obtain the Triforce which is shown at the very top left and right
在这里的幻灯片
of the slide here.
这是一个截图 塞尔达传奇的另一个截图
Here's a screenshot, another screen shot of Legend of Zelda,
在一个真正的地牢里 你可以在最上面看到
inside an actual dungeon where you can see at the very top,
有一个类似于地图的布局
there's got like a map layout.
地图在某种程度上是在网格中排列的
Maps are sort of arranged in a grid.
你可以一个房间一个房间地进去 这样每个房间都是整个宽度
And you could go in a room by room, whereby each room was the entire width
和屏幕高度 寻找 解决谜题 寻找物品
and height of the screen, looking for, solving puzzles, looking for items,
这类事情
that sort of thing.
你可以看到那里有一个怪物
You can see there's a monster there.
你们的心在最右上角
You have hearts at the very top right.
所以当你受到伤害时 心脏就会减少
So when you take damage, hearts sort of decrement.
会看到这两个方面 游戏的心和地牢的一面
Will see both of these, the hearts and the dungeon aspect of the game,
今天的讲座 以及房间的宽度和高度
today in lecture, as well as the width and height of the room
成为一块地牢瓷砖
being a dungeon tile.
以及控制一个化身
And controlling an avatar.
但这是一个有代表性的屏幕截图
But this is sort of a representative screenshot of what
这场比赛看起来像是回到了过去
the game looked like back in the day.
今天我们要讨论的一些话题
Some topics today that we'll be discussing in order
来实现像这样的游戏引擎的基础
to implement sort of the foundation for what a game engine like this
可能看起来像是自上而下的透视法
might look like are things like top down perspective.
如你所见 在这个截图中 我们
So as you can see, in this screenshot, we're
在鸟瞰视图中从最高处俯瞰林肯 与之相反
looking at Link from the very top in a bird's eye view, as opposed
到我们过去看马里奥的方式 从侧面 在哪里
to how we used to look at Mario, from the side, where
它有点像侧滚轴
it was sort of like a side scroller.
在这里 我们实际上是自上而下地看事情
Here we're actually looking at things from the top down.
所以我们以一种不同的视角来看待这个房间
So we have a view of the room in a sort of a different perspective.
从技术上讲 这并不是一个真正的z轴
There's not really a z axis, technically speaking.
但在某种程度上是有的
But there sort of is.
您可以在游戏引擎中实现像重力这样的东西 如下所示
You can implement things like gravity in a game engine like this
通过跳跃洞穴之类的方式
by jumping over holes and things like that.
但没有像《超级马里奥》那样的重力
But there's no gravity like there was in Super Mario,
当你从左向右走的时候 你会跳过缝隙
where you walk left to right, you jump over gaps,
从这个意义上来说 这是很容易看到的
and it's very easy to see in that sense.
我们将谈论无限的地牢世代
We'll be talking about infinite dungeon generation.
因此 在今天的例子中 我们将
So in the context of today's example, we'll
看看我们如何着手实施一个像你这样的地牢
see how we can go about implementing a dungeon that sort of you
可以永远持续下去 以及如何对其进行建模
can go through forever and ever, and how to sort of model that
让它看起来就像你一遍又一遍地穿过地牢
and make it look as if you're traveling through a dungeon over and over again.
在不同的房间里通过不同的屏幕 这些房间都是不同的
And going through different screens in different rooms that are all different.
但在现实中 我们会看到它实际上只是一个错觉 就像我们
But in reality, we'll see it's actually just an illusion like we've
在以前的课程中见过
seen before in prior lectures.
我们来谈谈打击手和伤兵手 还有什么？
Well talk about hitboxes and hurtboxes, and what
两者之间的区别在于
the difference is between the two.
希特盒是屏幕上的矩形 造成伤害
Hitboxes being rectangles on the screen that inflict damage
在您的游戏世界中的其他实体上 以及伤害盒
upon other entities in your game world, and hurtboxes
某种程度上是一个矩形 用来模拟你的玩家
sort of being the rectangle that models where your player,
或者游戏中的实体可能被其他命中框伤害的地方
or where an entity in the game can be hurt by other hit boxes.
好的 看看这些事件
Well look at events.
因此 事件是一种传播一些关键信息的方式 这些信息告诉
So events are a way of broadcasting some key message that tells
游戏世界哦 这件事发生了
the game world oh this thing happened.
并让我注册一个函数 以便在处理该事件时调用
And let me register a function to call when that event is processed.
因此 在某些事件上 调度一个事件 然后
So on some event, dispatch an event, and then
在该事件被监听它的任何东西接收时
upon that event being received by whatever is listening for it,
执行这段代码
perform this chunk of code.
它允许您在某种程度上分离游戏的各个方面
It allows you to sort of decouple aspects of your game
对引擎进行了一点改进 并使代码更具可读性
engine a little bit, and makes for a little bit more readable code.
并允许你用成就做一些有趣的事情
And allows you to do some interesting things with achievements,
例如 您不一定要拉动每一帧
for example, where you don't necessarily want to pull every single frame.
哦 我在这个框架里做了这种武断的事情清单吗？
Oh, did I do this sort of arbitrary list of things this frame?
相反 你可以通过一个事件来处理所有这些事情
Rather, you can just process all of that with an event,
有一个监听器和一个功能 每次你播放捡硬币的时候
and have a listener and a function that every time you broadcast pick up coin,
也许我的成就就像是
maybe I have an achievement that's like oh,
我是如何在这个关卡里捡到50枚硬币的
how I picked up 50 coins in this level.
然后 您的事件中的成就回调函数可以查找它
Your achievement callback function in your event can then look for that,
在你的游戏循环中 你不必说每一帧
and in your game loop, you don't have to say every frame,
如果一名玩家有850枚硬币 你可以说
if a player has 850 coins, and you sort of
通过这种方式去掉你整个游戏循环中可能存在的臃肿
take out bloat that would exist in your sort of overall game loop that way.
在今天的课程中 我们将看到一个如何使用它的例子
And we'll see an example of how we use that in today's lecture.
我们将查看屏幕滚动
We'll look at screen scrolling.
所以《塞尔达传奇》的一个非常标志性的方面
So a very iconic aspect of Legend of Zelda
就是当你从一个屏幕转到另一个屏幕时
is when you're going from one screen to another,
当一个屏幕加载而另一个屏幕加载时 会有一种过渡期
there is a sort of transition period as one screen loads and the other screen
就会消失
goes away.
在硬件上 在NES中 这是唯一的方法
In hardware, in the NES, this was sort of the only way
您实际上可以渲染超过一个屏幕宽度的瓷砖
you could actually render more than a screen width of tiles.
实际上 您必须动态加载切片并进行排序
You actually had to dynamically load in tiles and sort
覆盖在此之前存在于内存中的磁贴
of overwrite tiles that existed before that in memory.
但今天 我们将看看如何创造出
But today, we'll see how we can sort of create
只要画一间房间就能做到这一点的错觉
the illusion of doing that by just drawing a room
然后有了我们的主房间 然后就像是补丁一样
and then having our main room, and then just sort of tweening over,
然后将所有内容设置回原点为0.0
and then setting everything back to the origin at 0.0.
这让我们看起来就像是在
And it makes it look as if we're moving back and forth between all
这些房间 而实际上我们所做的只是换班
these rooms, when in reality all we're doing is just doing a shift,
然后把一切都恢复到0.0
and then putting everything back to 0.0.
所以 如果可以的话 我会在屏幕上说明这一点
So I'll illustrate that on the screen, if I can.
我们最后要讨论的一件事是数据驱动设计
And one of the last things we'll look at is data driven design.
在许多类型的游戏的背景下 特别是RPG和动作
In the context of a lot of types of games, particularly RPGs and action
在游戏中 能够为你所有的物品建模通常是非常有价值的
games, it's often very valuable to be able to model all of your items,
实体 某种能力 任何你真正想要的东西
entities, sort of abilities, anything you really
可以 作为数据而不是逻辑 为了让你更容易写一个
can, as data rather than logic, in order to make it easier for you to write one.
第二 你可以分配你游戏的设计方面
And two, for you to sort of allocate the design aspect of your game
给其他人 而不仅仅是程序员
to other people, not just programmers.
并有一个非常通用的发动机
And have an engine that's very versatile.
和模型 我们将看看我们是如何实现
And model and we'll take a look at how we implement
这在某种程度上为以后的研究奠定了基础
sort of a foundation for that later on.
但首先 我想为今天的课程演示一个演示
But first I'd like to illustrate a demo for today's lecture,
这是塞尔达传奇的一种实现
a sort of implementation of Legend of Zelda.
今天有没有人愿意来演示一下这个
Is there anybody that would like to come up and sort of demo this today
在课堂上？
in class?
太棒了
Awesome.
非常感谢
Thank you so much.
所以 只要你准备好了 就继续按那里的Return键
So whenever you're ready, go ahead and press the Return key there.
[音乐播放]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
所以我们在屏幕上看到 50岁的传奇 这是我们的塞尔达传奇
And so we see on the screen, Legend of 50, which is our Legend of Zelda
你敲竹杠
you rip off.
因此 您按Enter键
So you press Enter.
你进入 这就是游戏的发挥状态
You go into, this is the play state of the game.
所以你控制了一个化身
So you control an avatar.
你可以四处走走
You can walk around.
他可以与开关互动 就像我们在这里看到的那样
He can interact with switches, as we saw here.
当他按下开关时 门就会打开
When he presses a switch, the doors open.
一旦门打开了 你就可以走进去了
And once the doors are open, you can walk through them
而且 正如我之前提到的 它将屏幕转换为
and it does, as I alluded to before, it transitions the screen, one
整个屏幕的高度或宽度取决于向上和向下的方向
entire screen height or width, depending on the direction, up above and below.
我们现在看到 我们按空格键实际上是在挥舞我们的剑
We see here now where we're pressing spacebar to actually swing our sword.
它正在摧毁游戏空间中的实体
It's destroying the entities in the game space.
所以当你按下碰撞的空格键时会触发Hitbox
So there's a hitbox triggering when you press the space bar that collides
与游戏世界中的其他实体
with other entities in the game world.
如果希特箱击中了他们的伤害箱 那么他们就会被标记为死亡
If that hitbox hits their hurtbox, then they are flagged as dead,
他们从游戏世界中消失了
and they disappear from the game world.
所以这就是无止境的
And so this goes on ad infinitum.
这只是一个无尽的地牢
It's just an infinite dungeon.
这样他就可以进入我们想要的楼层之间
So he can go in-between as many floors as we want to.
我们所做的就是每次我们穿过一扇门 生出一个新房间
All we're doing is every time we go through a doorway, spawn a new room,
删除旧的 然后继续下去 永远
delete the old one, and just keep going forever, and ever, and ever.
在像塞尔达传奇这样的游戏中 它通常不会像这样工作
In a game like Legend of Zelda, it typically doesn't work like this.
有固定数量的房间 它们都以一种2D阵列的形式存在
There is a hard set number of rooms, and they all exist in sort of a 2D array.
当你产生你的地牢时 你可以说
And when you generate your dungeon, you sort of
必须考虑到我把钥匙放在哪里之类的事情
have to take into consideration things like where do I put the keys?
我该把老板放在哪里？
Where do I put the boss?
我该把宝藏放在哪里？
Where do I put treasure?
这类事情
That sort of thing.
我们不会太深入地讨论如何实现像这样的复杂算法
We won't get too in-depth as to how we can implement a complex algorithm like.
但我们会稍微谈一谈 也许会谈到一些想法
But we'll touch on it a little bit, and talk about maybe some ideas
这是我们拥有的
that we have.
最后 如果我们只是--如果我们想演示--
And then lastly, if we just-- if we want to demo--
如果我们能看到左上角 我们的心就在那里
if we can see the top left, we have hearts there,
这是塞尔达的标志性作品
which is iconic sort of Zelda.
当我们确实受到敌人的伤害时 注意到我们会有一点闪烁
When we do take damage from an enemy, notice that we flicker a little bit.
所以有一些渲染行为被触发
So there's some rendering behavior triggering,
当我们受到伤害时 我们就变得无懈可击
and we become invulnerable when we take damage.
最后 当我们终于接受最后一击的时候
And then lastly, when we finally take the last hit,
我们在屏幕上看到一个小游戏 使用的是塞尔达字体
we get a little game over screen, using the Zelda font.
简而言之 这就是游戏
And that's the game in a nutshell.
我们按Enter键并循环返回
We press Enter and loop back.
总体来说很简单 但有很多片段
So pretty simple altogether, but there's a lot of pieces
在这里 我们从来没有真正看到过
here that we haven't really seen before.
因此 非常感谢你们前来演示这款游戏
So thank you very much for coming up to demo the game.
好的
All right.
这就是《50岁的传奇》、《塞尔达传奇》的演示
So that was a demo of Legend of 50, Legend of Zelda.
它有很多塞尔达拥有的东西
It has a lot of the pieces that Zelda has.
当然 它还没有完全充实起来
It's not as fully fleshed out, of course,
作为像塞尔达这样的完整游戏 这将是一个巨大的游戏
as a full game like Zelda, which would be monstrously large.
我们还需要考虑很多因素
And there's a lot of things we need to factor in.
但基础就在那里
But the foundation is there.
我们有地牢的基础 我们可以在上面建造一个真正的发电机
We have the dungeon foundation upon which we can build an actual generator,
如果我们想的话
if we wanted to.
我们有实体
We have entities.
我们有命中率高的
We have hit boxes.
我们可以很容易地建模 因为我们在游戏中有开关
We could easily model, because we have switches in the game,
我们可以对宝物箱这样的东西进行建模
we could model things like treasure chests that
打开有不同的状态 就像开关有不同的状态一样
open that have different states, just like the switch had different states.
并让我们游戏空间中的不同对象与其他对象互动
And have different objects in our game space interact with other objects.
我们在这里有很多东西 今天我们将讨论所有的东西
We have a lot here, and we'll talk about all of it today.
这里有几个截图 只是为了展示我们刚刚看到的东西
So here's a few screenshots just to show what we just looked at.
我们的目标主要是第二个截图
Our goal mainly is the second screen shot,
在右上角 这是播放状态 它具有
on the top right, which is the play state, which has
我们刚刚看到的所有小碎片
all of the little pieces we just saw.
但为了把这一切联系起来 我们这里确实有一个开始状态
But just to tie it all together, we do have a start state here,
以及一场与国家相关的博弈
and a Game Over state which is relevant in regard
传到左上角的心脏
to the hearts on the top left.
所以我要谈的第一件事是 我们把发动机组装好了
So the first thing that I'll talk about as we sort of get the engine built up
是 我们要把我们的资产投入到游戏中去吗？
is, where do we go for getting our assets into the game?
就像之前的课程一样 在今天之前
And just like in prior lectures, prior to today,
我们只有一个精灵床单 就像我们对马里奥所做的那样
we just have a sprite sheet, like we did with Mario,
其中所有内容都以相当均匀的瓷砖分段顺序进行布局
where everything is laid out in a fairly even sequence of tile segments.
在本例中 线段为16x16像素
In this case, the segments are 16 by 16 pixels.
在这里 我叠加了一个网格 只是为了显示图片确实是完美的16
Here, I've overlaid a grid just to show that the picture is indeed perfectly 16
到16岁
by 16.
这是你应该考虑的事情
And this is something that you should take into consideration.
当你构建你的游戏资产时 你会有意识地这样做
And consciously do when you're building your game assets.
让它很容易被切成小块
Make it easy to chop up into little pieces,
这样你就可以通过一些四边形的表格来索引这个精灵了
so you can then index into this sprite via some table of quads.
然后为任何对象分配ID
And then assign an ID to whatever object,
或要渲染到屏幕上的平铺
or tile you want to render to the screen.
所以我们看到 如果你看这里 像门这样的东西
And so we see if you look here, things like the doors,
它们并不是由一块瓷砖完美地塑造出来的
they're not perfectly modeled by one tile.
所以当你有大于16乘以16的东西时
And so when you do have things that are larger than 16 by 16,
这并不像拥有具有该帧ID实体或对象那样简单
it's not quite as easy as oh have an entity or an object with this frame ID,
并将其绘制到屏幕上
and draw it to the screen.
您实际上需要稍微复杂一点的呈现逻辑
You actually need to a little bit more complicated render logic.
所以随便说说 如果我想画一扇门
So just offhand, if I wanted to draw a door,
有没有人对我如何建模有什么建议？
does anybody have any suggestions as to how I would model that?
或者把它画到屏幕上？
And or draw it to the screen?
因此 如果我们的门不是16x16像素的瓷砖
So if we have a door that's not perfectly a 16 x 16 pixel tile,
现在 我们需要做的就是存储所有四个
offhand, what we need to do is just basically store all four
在这种情况下 这些瓷砖 或至少跟踪有多少瓷砖
of those tiles in this case, or at least keep track of however many tiles
你的目标是
your object is.
然后只需根据一些偏移量绘制它们
And then just draw them based on some offset.
具有表示该对象左上角的XY
Have an xy that represents the top left of that object.
把它放在正确的位置 而不是只画一个瓷砖
Place it in the right position, and instead of drawing just one tile,
我们画了四块瓷砖
we draw four tiles.
然后 不是只有一个16乘16瓦的碰撞凸起
And then instead of having just one collision boss that's 16 by 16 tiles,
你可以做几件事
you can do a couple of things.
您可以检查所有四个瓷砖上的碰撞
You can either check collision on all four of these tiles,
或者至少是所有的两块门砖 或者是你自己定制的打印件
or at least all two of these door tiles, or model your own custom hit
然后 可能代表门口的对象可以控制的框
box that then maybe that object that represents a doorway has control of.
所以你可以说门口撞到了玩家 然后门口
So you can say doorway collides player, and then the doorway
它的高度和宽度是多少像素 它在这里是宽是高
has a height and width of however many pixels it is wide by tall here.
只有门的这一部分
Just this door part.
然后 您可以在不只有一块瓷砖的基础上构建
And then, you are able to then build upon not just having one tile that
在您的游戏空间中为对象或实体建模
models an object or entity in your game space,
但现在你有了更多的艺术灵活性
but now you have more artistic flexibility.
你可以做一些事情 比如有超过一个像素宽的门口
You can do things like have doorways that are more than one pixel wide.
因此 游戏世界变得更有说服力了
And sort of have a more convincing gameworld as a result of that.
你会在RPG这样的游戏中看到很多类似的东西
You'll see a lot of things like that in games like RPGs
在那里 你有满座的房子 显然不仅仅是一块瓷砖
where you have full houses that are obviously not just one tile.
如果你愿意 你可以用一块瓷砖来建模
You can model things as one tile if you want to,
但从艺术的角度 从游戏引擎的角度来看
but from an artistic perspective, and from just a game engine perspective,
它以编程方式更容易一些
it's a little bit easier to programmatically
能够将你所有的资产切成瓷砖 然后这样画出来
be able to cut up all your assets into tiles and draw them as such.
所以能够在单人精灵的基础上
So being able to build upon just the single sprite
并且能够用多个精灵来表示
and be able to do multiple sprites represent
物体是房屋、大树等事物的关键
an object is the key to things like houses, things like big trees,
比我们在这里看到的单一瓷砖更复杂的东西
things that are just more complicated than single tiles as we see here.
正如你所看到的 角色的精灵工作表有点复杂
The character sprite sheet is, as you can see, a little bit more complicated.
这是一个带有填充的精灵工作表的示例
So this is an example of a sprite sheet that has padding.
有时你会得到没有被整齐分割的精灵床单
Sometimes you will get sprite sheets that aren't neatly divided
分成偶数段
into even segments.
这是有充分理由的
And for good reason.
因为有时候你的瓷砖不是很完美
Because sometimes you have tiles that are not perfectly
游戏引擎的瓷砖的宽度和高度
the width and height of whatever your game engine's tiles are.
在这种情况下 播放器实际上是20像素高 16像素宽
In this case, the player is actually 20 pixels tall, and 16 pixels wide.
最重要的是 他有不同的动画画面
And on top of that, he's got different frames of animation.
我们可以在左下角看到 他有一个挥剑的动画
We can see here at the bottom left, he's got a sword swinging animation.
挥剑动画实际上存储在32×32像素的帧中
The sword swing animation is actually stored in a 32 by 32 pixel frame,
因为有时取决于他看的角度
because sometimes depending on which angle he's looking at,
他的精灵可以变大一点 也可以变小一点
his sprite can get a little larger or smaller.
所以当你有一个带衬垫的精灵 什么是一种
So when you have a sprite with padding, what's sort of a way
我们可以可靠地把这个画到屏幕上吗？
that we can draw this to the screen reliably?
我们该如何考虑这一点呢？
How do we take this into consideration?
我们将如何呈现带有填充的屏幕精灵？
How would we render a screen sprite with padding?
所以让我们假设这个精灵 我们的角色挥舞着一把剑 是在32
So let's say this sprite here, our character swinging a sword, is in a 32
乘以32像素框
by 32 pixel box.
对吗？
Right?
在这附近的这个盒子 这个空白空间
This sort of box around here, this white space.
但他仍然可能只有16个像素宽乘20个像素高
But he's only still maybe 16 pixels wide by 20 pixels tall.
或者 也许他在某种程度上与此类似
Or maybe he is some amount similar to that.
为了把他吸引到屏幕上 你可以在代码中看到
In order to draw him to the screen, which you can look at in the code,
我们真正需要做的就是为那个精灵分配一个偏移量
all we really need to do is assign that sprite an offset.
只要说 好的 这个精灵的偏移量x和偏移量
Just say, OK, this sprite's offset x and offset
Y是一些值 基本上可以让我们绘制精灵
y are some value that basically lets us draw the sprite
为负的x和负的y值
to a negative x and a negative y value.
这将使精灵向上移动 使其完美地对齐
And that'll shift the sprite up, such that it aligns perfectly
无论他的XY在哪里
with wherever his xy are.
您可以查看代码以了解它到底是如何工作的
And you can take a look at the code to see exactly how that works.
最后 我们游戏世界的实际实体是不同的生物
Lastly the actual entities for our game world are different creatures.
这是一张精灵图--这是一张更理想的精灵图
And this is a sprite sheet-- this is a more ideal sprite where everything
是16x16像素宽和高
is 16 by 16 pixels wide and tall.
我们在这里真正做的就是分好精灵床单
And all we really did here was just divide the sprite sheet
使用常规实用函数生成16个16的四边形
using the regular utility function generate quads by 16 16.
我们不必担心所有东西都有不同的宽度和高度
We don't have to worry about separate widths and heights for everything,
正因为如此 我们才能非常简单地制作动画
and we can create animations very simply because of this.
顺便说一句 当我在解析时 我喜欢做的事情
As a side note, something that I like to do, when I'm parsing
或者当我拼接一张有很多单独框架的精灵纸时
or when I'm piecing apart a sprite sheet that's got a lot of individual frames,
尤其是在我创作动画的时候 或者我只是
particularly if I'm creating animations, or I just
需要知道对于一个瓷砖 一个特定的瓷砖要画到屏幕上
need to know for a tile, a particular tile to draw to the screen.
手动查看每一块瓷砖是一种痛苦
It's kind of a pain to manually look through each and every tile, one
差一分
by one.
然后说好的 这是一个 但是好的
And say OK, this is one but OK.
但如果我想找出粘液是哪一种
But if I want to find out which one the slime is,
我数了一下 好的 这个有多少像素宽？
I got a count, OK how many pixels wide does this?
好的 然后是4乘以12
OK, and then it's times 4, it's 12.
然后它在第五排 所以12乘以4加1会得到 好的
And then it's on the fifth row, so 12 times 4 plus 1 will give me, OK.
所以它的指数是49
So it's at index 49.
所以我花了相当多的时间
So I've spent a non-trivial amount of time sort of hand
计算所有这些都做了什么
calculating what all these do.
我编写了一个简单的Python脚本 它只会遍历一个文件
I wrote a simple Python script that will just go over a file,
只需在每个单独的四元组中添加一个数字
and just add a digit to each individual quad,
让你一目了然地看到每个精灵是什么
to just show you at a glance what each sprite is.
这包括发行版 所以你可以看到它是什么样子的
And this is including the distro, so you can see what it looks like.
节省了很多时间
Saves a lot of time.
我建议尝试一下 当你在处理资产的时候
And I recommend trying, when you're sort of working with assets
你发现自己在做一件需要很长时间的事情
and you find yourself doing something that takes a long time,
这可能有点繁琐和机械
and it's sort of tedious and mechanical, maybe
试着找到一种自动化的方法 或者至少
try to find a way to sort of automate that, or at least
让事情变得更容易一目了然
make it easier to do things at a glance.
在这种情况下 只需简单地施加一个数字网格就可以解决这个问题
In this case, just simply imposing a numerical grid solves that problem.
我不需要花很多时间
I don't have to spend a significant amount of time
找出幽灵面向左侧的动画的哪一帧
figuring out which frames of animation the ghost facing left is.
我立刻就知道它是67、68和69 这让我可以把事情搞砸
I know instantly it's 67, 68 and 69, and allows me to just crank things
升得快得多
up that much faster.
所以我们首先要看的是一种自上而下的视角
So the first thing we'll take a look at is sort of top down perspective.
我们之前主要讨论过这个问题 早些时候
And we mostly talked about this before, earlier.
但它实际上只是一张我们以前见过的瓷砖地图
But all it really is is a tile map, which we've seen before.
唯一的不同是 现在不是从侧面看事情
The only difference is now, instead of looking at things from the side,
我们只是从上面看事情
we're just looking at things from up above.
那么最明显的考虑可能是什么呢？
So what's probably the most obvious consideration
在设计自上而下的透视图而不是侧边滚动时
when designing a top down perspective versus a sort of side scrolling
观点是什么？
point of view?
特别关注瓷砖是如何绘制的？
Looking at particularly at how the tiles are drawn?
最突出的是什么？
What stands out?
所以对我来说最突出的是我们
So the thing that stands out to me is that we
这里的墙壁上有影子之类的东西
have things like shadows on walls here.
我们也有角落 和所有的东西
We have also corners, and things altogether
是倾斜的 以至于它们几乎像是稍微旋转了一下 就好像它们
are skewed such that they are almost like rotated slightly as if they're
模拟相对于相机从上方朝上的旋转角度
simulating an angle of rotation relative to the camera facing from up above.
例如 你可以在播放器上看到这一点
You can see this on the player, for example.
看起来你是在上下打量他
It looks like you're looking at him from backwards and up.
当你以这种方式为你的资产建模时 它更有说服力
When you're modeling your assets that way, it's more convincing.
泽尔达总是这样做 让你的资产看起来
And Zelda has always done this, to make your assets look
就好像它们略微倾斜 你抬头看着上面
as if they are slightly tilted, and that you're looking up above.
所以当你设计一个自上而下的游戏时 只要
So when you're designing a top down game, just
为了令人信服 为了更有说服力 试着效仿一下
for convincing the sake of being more convincing, try and emulate that.
这里的实体 比如骨架 等等
The entities here, like the skeleton, and such,
更直截了当一点
are a little bit more straight on.
蝙蝠和泥巴之类的东西 尽管他们仍然
The bats and slimes and whatnot, even though they still
有一点那样的外表
have a little bit of that appearance.
就像蜘蛛一样 它看起来有点像是从上到后的
Like the spider it sort of looks as if it's from the top back.
但从自上而下的角度对你的资产进行建模 主要是这件事
But modeling your assets from a top down perspective, mainly the thing.
注意阴影和高光 它们
Pay attention to shadows and highlights, which
增加了很多方面 让我们相信我们是在这个有灯光的房间里
adds a lot in terms of convincing us that we're in this room with lighting.
还要确保你做的事情像是拐角之类的
And also make sure that you're doing things like corners and stuff
而且 它看起来似乎是稍微倾斜的旋转方向
and making, it look as if things are slightly skewed rotation wise.
我们要看的第一件事是发行版中的代码
The first thing that we're going to look at in terms of the code in the distro
就是地牢一代
is Dungeon Generation.
所以在塞尔达传说中 地下城是固定的
So in Legend of Zelda, dungeons are fixed.
它们完全是设计师事先设定的
They're completely set in advance by the designers.
在大多数游戏中 实际情况就是这样
And in most games, this is actually the case.
在我们的例子中 以及其他几个例子中
In our example, and in a couple of other examples,
其中一个主要的例子是我能想到的
a primary example of them being that I can think of,
我在幻灯片中看到了一个著名的游戏 叫做《艾萨克的装订》
that I have in the slides, a famous game called The Binding of Isaac,
也可以生成地下城
dungeons can also be generated.
那么 地下城的主单元是什么样的呢？
So what's the sort of like the main unit of a dungeon?
至少在《塞尔达传奇》的背景下是这样？
At least in the context of Legend of Zelda?
如果你必须提炼出地下城的组成成分
If you had to distill what comprises a dungeon,
最基本的单位是什么？
what's the most fundamental unit?
托尼
Tony.
一个房间
A room.
是
Yes.
一个房间
A room.
所以我们几乎可以看到这一点 如果我们用2D阵列来描述它
So we can almost look at this, if we picture it in terms of a 2D array,
对吗？
right?
我们有 假设这类似于指数1.1
We have, assuming that this is like index 1.1
在Lua中是0.0 在其他语言中是从左到右、从上到下
in Lua, 0.0 in other languages, going left to right, top to bottom.
基本上 我们有开或关 相对于每一个
Basically we have on or off, relative to each of these.
关 开 关
Off, on, off, off, off.
这个2D数组中的每个索引都有一个空间
Each of the indexes in this 2D array holds a room.
因此 这个房间在其他房间之间有隐含的联系
And so the room has connections implicitly between the other rooms.
如果你想去 比方说 从这个房间到这个房间
If you wanted to go, let's say, from this room here to the room
在它上面 就2D数组而言 偏移量是多少？
up above it, what's the offset, in terms of the 2D array?
我们要怎么从这个房间走到这个房间？
How are we going from this room up to this room?
所以我们只是上升了一级 对吗？
So we're just going up a y level, right?
这是x级3 y级3
So this is x level 3, y level 3.
如果我们想上到隔壁房间 我们需要上车
If we wanted to go up to the next room, we need to load in.
如果我们用泽尔达的方式来做 对吗？
If we're doing it the Zelda way, right?
我们只是要去--
And we're just going--
我们在一个房间和一个房间之间做过渡
we're doing a transition between one room
对另一个人来说 我们需要做的就是在这个房间里装东西
to another, what we need to do is load in the room at this room,
在y上减去1 然后执行转换
minus one on the y, and then perform the transition.
然后将其设置为当前房间 例如
And then set that to the current room, such
现在我们知道我们处于y水平2 x水平3
that now we know we're at y level 2, x level 3.
那是我们的地牢
That's our dungeon.
在塞尔达传说中的2D地下城的背景下
In the context of 2D dungeons in The Legend of Zelda,
这就像它的实际情况一样简单
that's as simple as it really is.
你有一个由地牢房间组成的2D网格
You have a 2D grid of dungeon rooms.
每个房间都有自己的实体和对象集合
Each room has its own collection of entities and objects
以及与其他房间的联系
and connections to other rooms.
但实际上 填充地牢所要做的就是以一种智能的方式填充数组
But really, all you do to fill a dungeon is fill an array in a smart way
使得不存在例如它们自己留下的房间
such that there is no rooms that are, for example, left by themselves.
请注意 地牢中的每个房间都至少有一个连接
Notice that every room in the dungeon has at least one connection
去另一个房间
to another room.
当你在做你的算法时
And that when you're maybe doing your algorithm
为了创造一个令人信服的地下城 让我们假设这里的这个房间有
to create a convincing dungeon, let's say this room here has
右边有一扇门 门上有锁
a door on the right, that has a lock.
对吗？
Right?
我们要确保钥匙不在那个房间里
We want to make sure that the key isn't in that room.
因为如果是的话 我们永远都不会是
Because if it is, we're never going to be
能够到达它 假设我们来自另一个方向
able to get to it, assuming that we come from another direction.
所以当你按程序设计地牢时
So when you're designing dungeons procedurally,
你想把这些事情都考虑进去
you want to take these sort of things into consideration.
然后 例如 老板的房间
And then for example, the boss room.
假设这是老板的房间 老板的房间
Let's say this is the boss room, the boss room
应该有一把老板的钥匙之类的
should have maybe a boss key, or something like that.
但显然 老板的钥匙不应该在那个房间里
But the boss key should not be, obviously, in that room.
它应该在某个地方 也许前面还有几个房间
It should be somewhere maybe where there's a couple of rooms before it
有一把锁或一把钥匙 这样你就知道有某种挑战
that have a lock or a key, so that you know there's some sort of challenge
卷入了你的地牢
involved in your dungeon.
这不是像我们以前做的那样只是随机的
It's not just random as we've done before.
必须有一些有意识的设计来代表
There has to be a little bit of sort of conscious design on behalf
你的算法
of your algorithms.
今天我们做的事情完全是随机的
Today we're doing things completely random
作为说明 仅仅因为像这样的系统是相当健壮和复杂的
for illustration, just because a system like this is fairly robust and complex.
但只要付出一些努力 您就可以创建一个简单的地下城生成器
But with some effort, you could create a simple dungeon generator just using
那些机械师
those mechanics.
只要确保你锁上门就行了
Just make sure that you have locked doors.
只有当你有钥匙时 锁着的门才能打开
The locked doors can only open when you have a key.
确保钥匙放在可以接近的地方
Make sure the key exists in a place that's accessible,
并在某种程度上创建了一个控制流的链
and sort of create a chain of a control flow.
模型可以通过某种图形来表示你的地牢
Model maybe via graph of some kind that represents your dungeon,
以及它的进程
and the progression thereof.
这就是塞尔达地牢的样子
So that's what a Zelda dungeon looks like.
这就是2D地牢在这种视角下的样子
That's what a 2D dungeon in this sort of perspective looks like.
而且它看起来--它看起来会和其他游戏引擎中的类似
And it looks-- it will look similar to this in other game engines.
它不一定要被完美地建模
It doesn't necessarily have to be perfectly modeled
作为一个屏幕宽度 屏幕高度空间变成另一个屏幕宽度 屏幕
as a screen width, screen height room going into another screen width, screen
房间很宽敞
wide room.
您可以拥有任意复杂的房间 这些房间的大小可以任意复杂
You can have arbitrarily complex rooms that have arbitrarily complex sizes
和形状
and shapes.
但你仍然需要确保房间外的连接
But you still need to make sure that the connections going out of the rooms,
如果你还能做左、右、上、下的模型 如果你想的话
like if you can still model left, right, up, down, if you want to.
您可以对房间之间的任意数量的连接进行建模
You can model arbitrary numbers of connections between rooms.
只要确保你有可以解决的谜题
Just make sure that you have puzzles that can be solved.
这是产生你的地下城的主要障碍
That's the main sort of obstacle in generating your dungeons.
这是一款我非常喜欢的游戏 它使用了塞尔达传奇的古老公式
Here's a game that I really like that uses the old Legend of Zelda formula
现在效果非常好
to very good effect now.
这叫做《以撒的捆绑》
It's called The Binding of Isaac.
请注意 我们已经可以立即看到它是自上而下的透视图
Notice already we can instantly see that it's top-down perspective.
整个房间的宽度和高度都是--
It's the entire width and height of the room is the dungeon of--
整个屏幕的宽度和高度都是地下城的房间
the entire width and height of the screen is the dungeon room.
这里有一张地图 上面显示 好的 我就在这个房间里
You have a map up here that shows you, OK, I'm in this room right here.
我可以上去 我可以往左走
I can go up, I can go left.
我可以向右走 我可以往下走
I can go right, I can go down.
上面这个黄色皇冠的房间 那是
This room up here with the yellow crown, that's
会被锁在某个门后面 拿着钥匙
going to be locked behind some door with a key.
所以我们需要有在这些房间里产生的钥匙
So we need to have keys that spawn in any of these rooms that
只是盲目地接近而已
are just blindly accessible.
艾萨克做事情的方式也有点不同
And Isaac does things a little bit differently also
因为它随机生成密钥和炸弹
in that it generates keys and bombs randomly,
这样你就可以真正得到--
so that you can actually get--
你不一定要把钥匙放在非常特定的位置
you don't necessarily have to plant your keys in very specific locations,
如果您的算法足够灵活和足够复杂
if your algorithm is sufficiently accommodating and complex enough.
你可以在每个房间的尽头 有机会随机产生一把钥匙
You can just at, the end of every room, have a chance to spawn a key randomly.
如果你幸运 或者如果你不幸运 假设
And if you're lucky, or if you're not lucky, and assuming
地牢的尽头并不存在于你锁着的门后面
that the end of the dungeon doesn't exist behind your locked doors.
你有机会拖延并锁上那些门 或者不
You have the opportunity to stall and lock those doors, or not.
并在需要的时候穿过你的地牢
And just go on through your dungeon as needed.
在这种情况下 他们不会锁上老板的门
In this case, they don't lock the boss doors.
这样 无论你有没有钥匙 你都可以通过老板的门
So you can go through the boss door regardless of whether you have a key.
所以他们已经适应了这种纯粹随机的方法
So they've accommodated for this purely random approach,
这正好说明了你如何仍然可以采取随机化
and that just goes to illustrate how you can still take randomisation
使用非常复杂的原理 并制作游戏
using very complex principles, and produce games
非常令人上瘾和有趣的东西
that are extremely addicting and fun.
而且你也不一定要非常详细
And you don't necessarily need to be super elaborate.
第一件事 好的
The first thing, OK.
因此 热门话题和伤害性话题将成为下一个话题
So hitboxes and hurtboxes will be the next topic.
所以 我想在代码中谈一谈 我们是如何在地下城
So I want to touch on, in the code, how we sort of do dungeon
这是游戏引擎中的一代
generation in the game engine here.
所以我要敞开心扉
So I'm going to open up--
有几份文件
there's a few files.
请注意 在源代码发行版中 有一个World文件夹
So doorway, notice in the source distro, there's a World folder.
我们已经对所有的文件进行了分类
We've sort of categorized all of the files that
与那个World文件夹中的世界一代有关
have to do with world generation within that World folder.
我们有一份门口档案 一份地牢档案 还有一份房间档案
We have a doorway file, we have a dungeon file, and we have a room file.
因此 地牢文件对地牢进行了建模
So the dungeon file models the dungeon.
所有形成我们地牢的房间 就像一个非常高的 水平的顶层
All of the rooms that form our dungeon, just as a very high, level top
级别、数据结构
level, data structure.
其实很简单
It's actually very simple.
正如我们之前看到的 这个房间是地牢的个体单位
The room is, as we saw before, the individual unit of the dungeon.
因此 地牢实际上就像一张房间的桌子
So a dungeon is effectively like a table of rooms.
然后它保存着我们如何在它们之间转换的代码
And then it holds the code for how we can transition between them.
但这在某种程度上是我们可以思考的
But that's sort of how we can think about it.
当你的游戏水平一般时 在这种情况下是地下城
When you a game level in general, in this case dungeon
在某种程度上是我们的比赛水平
is sort of our game level.
您可以对不同的子集方面建模
You can model the different subset aspects
通过某种数据结构来了解你的水平
of your level via some data structure.
在这种情况下 我们决定把它腾出空间
In this case, we've decided to make it room.
但如果你只有一个平台或关卡
But if you have just a platform or level,
也许你有区域或区域 或任何东西
maybe you have regions or zones, or anything.
只是你所在级别的一些小部分 你可以在它们之间过渡
Just little subsegments of your level that you can transition between.
从这个角度考虑是很有用的 因为从效率来看
It's useful to think in terms of that, because from an efficiency
从性能的角度来看 您希望动态加载
and performance standpoint, you want to dynamically probably load
特定的级别 一次一个
certain levels one at a time.
某些方面 某些部分 你所在水平的子领域 一次一个
Certain aspects, certain components, sub areas of your level, one at a time,
而不是一次只有整个级别
rather than just the entire level at once,
因为这取决于你的关卡有多复杂和多大
because depending on how sufficiently complex and large your level is,
您可以开始练习您的计算机的内存限制
you can get to exercising your computer's memory constraints.
所以我不想这么做
So don't want to do that.
所以在这种情况下 我们的算法是我们有一个地牢 我们有房间
So in this case, our algorithm is we have a dungeon, we have rooms.
我们有一个活动房间 只能在同一时间看到 那是
We have one active room that's only visible at one time that's
加载到内存中
loaded in memory.
然后每当我们在不同房间之间转换时
And then whenever we transition between rooms,
我们想要另一间临时入住的房间
we want to have another room that gets temporarily loaded.
那么让我们来看看这里的地下城班级
So let's look at the dungeon class here.
地下城 卢亚
Dungeon.lua.
所以14间自学的房间 空着桌子
So 14 self-taught rooms, empty table.
我们要在里面放满房间 就是房间里的东西
We're going to fill that with rooms, just room objects.
自助室
Self.currentroom.
房间 我们要把它传给球员
Room, and we're going to pass it in the player.
从而玩家可以访问其中的所有实体和对象
So that the player has access to all the entities and objects therein,
可以做碰撞检测之类的事情 这是非常重要的
and can do things like collision detection, which is very important.
也是为了让房间里的实体可以看到玩家
And also so that the entities in the room can look at the player
然后决定他们想要对他们的人工智能做什么
and then decide what they want to do with their AI, which
您可以对任意复杂的模型进行建模
you can model arbitrarily complex.
Room.lua的整个初始化函数都在运行 我们将在这里展示它
The whole init function of room.lua is going, we're going to show it here.
所以在room.lua中 在同一个World文件夹中
So in room.lua, in that same world folder,
我们已经在高级别实例化了地牢
we've instantiated the dungeon at a high level.
我们知道地牢 它基本上是一张桌子的房间
We know the dungeons, it's basically a table of rooms.
那么房间是什么样子的呢？
So what's a room look like?
嗯 一个房间 就像我们以前看到的 有哪些部分
Well a room, as we saw before, what are the pieces
一个房间需要什么才能发挥作用？
that a room needs in order to function?
在某种程度上 房间需要控制什么？
What does the room have to sort of keep control of?
观众：门
AUDIENCE: Doors.
科尔顿·奥格登：门
COLTON OGDEN: Doors.
还要别的吗？
Anything else?
所以它必须跟踪门 对吗？
So doors it has to keep track of, right?
因为当我们触摸一扇门时 我们应该过渡到另一个房间
Because when we touch a door, we should transition to the next room.
它应该跟踪玩家
It should keep track of the player.
这样玩家就可以更新了
So the player can update.
它应该跟踪房间里的物体 比如开关
It should keep track of objects in the room like switches,
正如我们在示例中看到的 这样他们就可以更新那些
as we saw in the example, such that they can update those.
看看这位选手踩到开关了吗？
And see has the player stepped on the switch?
如果他有 就把门打开
If he has, open the doors.
然后是实体 对吗？
And then entities, right?
它应该跟踪房间里的所有生物
It should keep track of all of the creatures in the room
这样他们就可以更新 他们可以相互互动
so that they can update, they can interact with each other.
球员可以打他们 或者他们可以打球员
The player can hit them, or they can hit the player.
您可以对任何您想要的交互进行建模
And you can model whatever interactions you want to.
所以我们可以在这里看到
So we can see here.
哦 还有一件事
Oh, and another thing too.
可能是它更重要的视觉方面之一
Probably one of the more important visual aspects of it,
我们还需要一套瓷砖来模拟房间的样子
we need to also have a set of tiles that model what the room looks like.
这是一个集装箱
It's a container.
所以我们要画 我们有一个角 一个角
So we're going to draw, we have a corner, a corner, a corner, a corner.
两边都是墙
Walls on the sides.
顶部和底部的墙
Walls on the top and bottom.
然后是一层楼
And then a floor.
所以我们显然需要画出房间
And so we need to obviously draw the room
在我们画出所有其他的东西之前 更新所有其他的东西
before we draw all of the other things, and update all the other things.
因此 瓷砖、门口、实体和对象
So tiles, doorways, entities, and objects.
所以我们可以在这里看到
So we can see here.
你有瓷砖 柔和的瓷砖靠在一张空桌子上
You have tiles, soft-lit tiles against an empty table.
我们有一个叫做生成墙和楼板的功能
We have a function called Generate Walls And Floors.
实体、空表
Entities, empty table.
我们有一个名为生成实体的函数
We have a function called Generate Entities.
然后对象就等于空桌了
And then objects equals empty table.
我们有一个名为生成对象的函数
We have a function called Generate Objects.
最后是门口
And lastly, doorways.
然后是这里 因为它不一定
And then here because it's not necessarily
就像我们需要一个完整的功能一样复杂 我们只有四个门
as complex as we need for a entire function, we just have four doorways.
这是静态的
And this is static.
在本例中 我选择始终保留所有的门口
I've chosen in this example to have all the doorways always
处于相同的位置 并以相同的方式行事
be in the same place, and sort of behave in the same way.
但您可以创建一个更复杂的系统 特别是
But you could create a more complex system, whereby especially
如果你有一个动态生成地牢的算法
if you have an algorithm that generates a dungeon dynamically,
也许你的房间不一定是硬性的
and maybe your rooms aren't necessarily hard set.
也许你有一把扫帚 对吧？
Maybe you have a broom, right?
如果我们早点回到我们的幻灯片
If we go back to our slides earlier.
让我们假设我们看的是这个房间 就在这个最中间的地方
And let's say we're looking at this room right here in the very center.
我们可以看到它的左边有一个门 上面有一个门
We can see it has a doorway on the left, a doorway up top,
右手边还有一扇门
and a doorway to the right.
但它的底部没有通道
But there's no doorway on the bottom.
这看起来像是代表设计师的一个武断的设计决定
And that looks like an arbitrary design decision on behalf of the designers.
但如果我们看看上面的这个房间 我们
But if we look at this room up top here, we
可以看到它在某种程度上是以同样的方式运行的
can see that it sort of behaves in the same way.
左边有一扇门通往这个房间
There's a doorway going into this room to the left.
下面有一个通往这个房间的门道
There's doorway going to this room down below.
但上面没有门 右边也没有门
But it doesn't have a doorway up top and a doorway on the right,
因为那个房间和那些方向之间没有房间
because there are no rooms going between that room and those directions.
所以当你有一个二维地牢房间阵列时
So when you have a 2D array of dungeon rooms,
你想要为你的门口建模 它可以很简单
and you want to model your doorways, it can be as simple
那么 那个方向还有空间吗？
as is there room in that direction?
如果有 您将拥有您的数据结构
If there is, and you will have your data structures sort of
在生成这些门口之前预先布置好 如果它不存在
laid out in advance before you generate these doorways, if it does not exist,
不要做一扇门
don't make a door.
如果它确实存在 就做一扇门
If it does exist, make a door.
然后确保当你过渡的时候
And then make sure that when you transition
从右到左 或者从下到上
between from the right to the left, or from the bottom to the top,
您可以在2D房间阵列中以正确的索引进入正确的房间
that you go to the correct rooms at the correct indices in your 2D room array.
这说得通吗？
Does that make sense?
到目前为止 有没有人有什么问题想知道这是如何在高层运作的？
Anybody have any questions so far as to like how this works at a high level?
好的?
OK?
太棒了
Awesome.
所以这里的这些门道都是因为这座地牢
So these doorways here are all because of this dungeon
是完全随机的 每次它总是有通向顶部和底部的门
is completely random, and every time it always has doorways going top, bottom,
左手和右手
left and right.
我们总是要放四扇门
We're always just going to put four doorways,
从上 下 左 右
going top, bottom, left and right.
请注意 它们接受一个字符串 表示
Note that they take a string denoting which
它们是方向 这将变得重要
direction they are, and this will become important
稍后在Doorway课程中 我们在这里看到
later on in the doorway class, which we see here
被建模为单独的类
is modeled as a separate class.
这里的FALSE只是意味着门是开着的吗？
False here just means is the door open?
因此 默认情况下 我们将关闭门
So by default, we're going to close the door.
然后是自己 这样我们就可以从门口进入房间
And then self, so that we have access to the room from the doorway.
房间里应该有球员的名字
The room should have a reference to the player,
这样它就可以对实体和玩家之间的交互进行建模
so that it can model interactions between the entities and the player,
以及物品和球员
as well as the objects and the player.
请注意 它具有渲染偏移
Notice that it has a render offset.
所以如果我们看看这个游戏 瓷砖
So if we look at the game here, the tiles
不要与屏幕的宽度和高度完全匹配
don't completely match up to the width and height of the screen.
这主要是虚拟高度的函数
And that's mainly a function of the virtual height
没有完美地映射到16个瓷砖 由16个瓷砖均匀划分
not mapping perfectly to 16 tiles, divided evenly by 16 tiles.
所以我所做的就是把地牢变小了一点
So what I've done is I've made the dungeon a little bit smaller.
还有一个事实是 门口占据了几块额外的衬垫
And also the fact that the doorways take up a couple of extra tiles of padding
在他们的一侧 这里就像是一片空白
on their sides, it's like sort of blank space up here.
我们已经将所有东西都稍微向内移动了一点
We've shifted everything inwards a little bit.
我们已经把地牢做了两块 宽度和高度都比屏幕小
We've made the dungeon two tiles smaller width and height wise than the screen.
然后我们呈现了一定数量的偏移量
And then we've just rendered offset by a certain amount
使其完全居中
such that it's completely centered.
我们计算在完全渲染的地下城之间存在多少填充
We calculate how much padding exists between the fully rendered dungeon
不管剩下什么空格 只要移动一半就行了
and whatever blank space is left, and just shift by half of that amount,
这是我们的渲染偏移量
and that's our render offset.
因此 这就是渲染偏移在这种情况下很重要的原因
So that's why render offset is important in this case.
当你试图将任何东西放在中心时 你通常会
When you're trying to center anything, you typically
只需计算一个偏移量即可
do it just by calculating an offset.
计算你想要画的任何东西的宽度和高度
Calculate the width and height of whatever you're trying to draw,
计算屏幕的宽度和高度减去它
calculate whatever your width and height of your screen is minus that,
将其除以2 这就是渲染偏移
divide it by 2, that's your render offset.
这里的这两个领域很有趣 自邻接偏移X
And then these two fields here are interesting. self.adjacentoffsetX,
Self.adjectoffsetY
self.adjectentoffsetY.
有没有人猜到这是用来做什么的？
Does anybody have a guess as to what this is used for?
嗯
Yeah.
当它在隔壁房间的时候画自己
Drawing itself when it's the adjacent room.
是的 没错
Yes, exactly.
所以当它在隔壁房间的时候画自己
So drawing itself when it's the adjacent room.
所以当你装上下一个房间的时候 你要
So when you load the next room, you're going
实例化一个房间 就像这样
to instantiate a room just like this.
但默认情况下 它将绘制为0.0
But by default it's going to draw at 0.0.
然而 如果我们想要那个房间画在我们不合适的地方
However, if we want that room to draw not right where we are.
显然 如果我们在现在的房间里 我们
Obviously, if we're in the current room, we
我不想让隔壁的房间画在最上面
don't want the next room drawing right on top
我们所处的位置 因为那样它就会层次分明
of where we are, because then it's just going to layer right
在我们所在的房间顶端
on top of the room we're in.
我们想把它画出来--
And we want to draw it--
如果我们要向右转 则需要向右绘制屏幕宽度
if we're going to the right, we want to draw a screen width to the right.
如果我们将其绘制到左侧 我们希望将其绘制为左侧的屏幕宽度
If we're drawing it to the left, we want to draw it a screen width to the left.
在y轴上也是一样的
And same thing on the y-axis.
上方或下方的屏幕高度
A screen height above, or below it.
所以相邻的偏移量X或y 我们在画房间的时候加进去就行了
So adjacentoffsetX or y, we just add to when we draw the room.
这将产生与房间分开渲染的效果
And that'll have the effect of rendering it separately from the room
我们目前所处的位置
that we're currently in.
我可以试着在这里画一个插图
I can try and draw an illustration here.
所以 如果我们有我们的房间 这就是我们现在的房间
So if we have our room here, this is our current room.
太自私了 房间里
So self.currentroom.
假设我们在这里有一扇门
And let's say we have a doorway here.
对吗？
Right?
那是一个门口的物体 玩家在这里
That's a doorway object, the player is here.
他撞上了那个物体
He collides with that object.
它会触发一个过渡到上面的房间
It's going to trigger a transition to a room up above.
所以我们要做的就是马上搬进一个新房间
So what we do is we load in a new room right away.
我们总是有一个名为self.nextroom的指针
We always have a pointer called self.nextroom.
这些都记录在dungeod.lua文件中
And this is all kept track of in the dungeod.lua file.
但在默认情况下 self.nextroom将为零
But self.nextroom by default is going to be nil.
但是当我们从现在的房间过渡到下一个房间的时候 对吗？
But when we transition from the current room to the next room, right?
我们应该把它设置成某种东西
We should set that to something.
因此 self.Curentroom将是相同的
So self.currentroom is going to be the same.
但当我们触发这场碰撞时
But when we trigger this collision, self.nextroom,
这将只相当于一个新房间
this is going to be equal to just a new room.
然后我们就知道我们在哪个门口了
And then we get which doorway we're in.
我们会想办法的
We figure it out.
从技术上讲 我们会弄清楚我们要朝哪个方向前进
We figure out which direction we're moving in, technically.
然后如果我们往上走 我们就会通过一个--
And then if we're moving up, then we just pass in a--
在这种情况下 我们说它与负屏幕高度的偏移量y相邻
we said it's adjacent offset y in this case, to negative screen height.
如果它低于屏幕高度 则将其设置为正屏幕高度
If it's below, we set it to positive screen height.
如果我们到这里 它将是负屏 与相邻的x
If we go here, it's going to be negative screen with the adjacent x,
将为负屏宽
will be negative screen width.
如果我们向右移动 那么x上的正屏幕宽度
And then positive screen width on the x if we're moving to the right.
所以我们可以看到这种相邻的 如果是XY
And so this sort of adjacent we could see, if do xy,
这基本上就是相邻的偏移量
it will be that's basically the adjacent offset.
最后我们画出了从底部到
And so we end up when we draw our transition going from bottom to
在这种情况下 我们只是补间相机到这个值
up in this case, we just tween the camera to this value.
我们有摄像头 对吧？
So we have a camera, right?
这是我们的相机
This is our camera.
默认情况下它会看这里 摄像机x和摄像机y
And it's going to be looking here by default. So camera x and camera y,
这些也是我们代码中的价值观
those are values in our code as well.
当我们在门口触发碰撞时
When we trigger this collision on the doorway,
这里有当前的空间 它是0.0
and we have current room here, which is at 0.0,
这里有一个房间 它的位置是0加上相邻的
and then we have this room here, which is at 0 plus our adjacent
偏移y 这是负的屏幕高度
offset y, which is negative screen height.
所以它的作用是使屏幕高度在y轴上为负
So it has the effect of making it negative screen height on the y.
我们的相机x回忆爱 图形 翻译是我们的相机
Our camera x recall love.graphics.Translate is our camera.
所以我们要做的就是在两者之间
So all we do is we just tween that.
我们说 好的
We say, OK.
这是我们的X号摄像机会在这里.
Here's our Cam x is going to be here.
小卡 有点乱了
And Cam y, it's getting a little bit messy.
我道歉
I apologize.
但是我们的x和y摄像头在这里
But our camera x and y are here.
随着时间的推移 我们会把它放到下一个房间
And then over time, we're going to tween that up into the next rooms
x和y 即x加上相邻偏移x y加上相邻偏移y
x and y, which is a just x plus adjacent offset x, y plus adjacent offset y.
一旦摄像机从这里移到这里
And then once this camera has shifted from here up to here,
或者我们要去的任何方向 无论是上 下 左还是右
or whichever direction we're going, whether it's up, down, left or right.
一旦我们完成了这一点 我们可以再次将所有内容标准化为0.0
Once we've completed that, we can normalize everything again back to 0.0
我们需要做的是
by doing self.currentroom equals, what do we need to do,
如果我们要把所有东西都放回去
if we're going to put everything back to?
假设我想把这个房间设为新的当前房间
Let's say I want to make this room the new current room.
我需要做什么？
What do I need to do?
我们有当前房间 还有下一个房间
So we have current room, and we have next room.
如果我想让当前房间变成下一个房间
If I want the current room to become the next room,
我只需要说self.currencial等于self.nextreme 对吧？
all I need to do is say self.currentroom equals self.nextroom, right?
一旦发生这种情况
And then once that happens, what happens to the adjacent
下一个房间的x和y偏移量
offset x and y of the next room?
他们被设置为0 对吧？
They get set to 0, right?
我想把这个房间 我们已经抵消了这里
I want to take this room that we've offset up here,
我只想让它再次成为游戏世界的中心
and I just want to make it the center of the game world again.
我只想把它设置为0.0 这样我们就可以进行完全相同的计算
I want to just put it as 0.0, so we can do this exact same calculation
只需将相邻的偏移量x或y设置为负或正屏幕高度
by just setting adjacent offset x or y to a negative or positive screen height
或相对于0.9的屏幕宽度
or screen width relative to 0.9.
所以我要做的就是设置相邻的偏移量
So what I'm going to do is just set the adjacent offset
将下一个房间(即当前房间)的x和y设置为0
of x and y of the next room, which is now current room, to 0.
它会把它拉回到0.0
And it's going to draw it right back at 0.0.
然后 相机x和相机y也将设置为0.0
And then camera x and camera y are also going to be set to 0.0.
这将会产生一种效果 看起来就像我们正在上升
And this is going to have the effect of looking as if we're going up
并留在那里
and staying there.
但在现实中 我们只是往上走 然后
But in reality, we're just going up, and then
立刻把一切都调回到了0度
instantly shifting everything back to 0.0,
包括那个房间的玩家、实体和开关
including the player, entities, and switches of that room.
所以这纯粹是一种错觉
So it's purely an illusion.
但它允许我们模拟这种无限探索地牢效应的过程
But it allows us to simulate this sort of infinite exploring a dungeon effect.
这说得通吗？
Does that make sense?
这种工作方式的整体流程是否有意义？
Does the overall flow of how this works makes sense?
好的
OK.
所以那里有点乱
So it's a little bit messy there.
希望我能够说明整个算法是如何
Hopefully I was able to illustrate the overall algorithm for how
无限地牢发电机起作用了
the infinite dungeon generator works.
我们在哪里停下来了？
Where did we leave off?
我们在房间的初始功能中
We were in the init function of the room.
因此 让我们来看看组成它的几个函数
So let's take a look at a few of the functions that comprise that.
因此 生成墙和地板
So generate walls and floors.
这与我们所看到的非常相似
This is very similar to what we've looked
以马里奥的瓷砖地图为例 我们只需从y到x
at before with tile maps in Mario for example, where we just go from y to x.
然后我们只需要选择一个随机的ID 或者我们的随机ID
And then we just pick a random ID, or our random ID.
嗯 其中一些是随机的身份证
Well, it is random ID for some of it.
但有时我们需要一个明确的身份证明
But sometimes we need an explicit ID.
所以提醒我 ID实际上映射到什么时候
So remind me, what does the ID actually map to when
我们要把瓷砖画到屏幕上吗？
we're you drawing tiles to the screen?
如果我们想给一块瓷砖一个ID 那是什么 它应该映射到什么？
If we want to give a tile an ID, what does that, what should that map to?
嗯?
Yeah?
观众：精灵纸上的画框
AUDIENCE: The frame in the sprite sheet.
科尔顿·奥格登：精灵图中的画框 没错
COLTON OGDEN: The frame in the sprite sheet, that's correct.
并不是所有的游戏引擎、所有的实现都必须如此
It doesn't have to for all game engines, for all implementations.
但这是最容易做的事情 只需给您的切片一个ID
But it's the easiest thing to do, is just to give your tile an ID
然后你就可以画出来 你可以编制索引
that you can then just draw, you can index
在你的精灵单子上用那个ID
into your sprite sheet at that ID.
这是一种非常、非常简单、轻巧、干净的建模方法
It's just very, very simple, lightweight clean approach to modeling.
我们可以在这里看到 ID得到了ID
And we can see here, ID gets ID.
在我们弄清楚我们想要什么ID之后 现在如何
After we've figured out what ID we want, now how
我们是不是决定了 比如说我想画--
do we determine like let's say I want to draw--
比方说 就像这块瓷砖
let's say, for example, like this tile here.
请注意 这是一块角瓷砖
Notice it's a corner tile.
我需要做什么才能基本上分配--
What do I need to do to basically assign--
我甚至在有机会给你看之前就要死了
I'm going to die before I even have the chance to show you.
在我躲避敌人的同时 如果我想画左上角
While I avoid enemies, if I wanted to draw that top left corner,
我要找的是什么？
what am I sort of looking for?
不管怎么说 我还在承受损失
I'm still taking damage anyway.
相对于x和y 我要找的是什么？
Relative to x and y, what am I looking for?
假设那块瓷砖需要多少x和y
What x and y does that tile need, assuming
一切从左上角的1.1开始 然后向下
everything starts 1.1 on the top left, and goes down
整个地牢的高度和宽度？
to height and width of the overall dungeon?
左上角的XY需要是什么？
What is the xy need to be of that top left corner?
它应该是1 对吗？
It needs to be 1, right?
所以如果是1.1 基本上就是左上角
So if that's 1.1, basically the top left corner,
该ID应等于角子画面
that ID should be equal to the corner sprite.
特别是左上角的精灵
The top left corner sprite, specifically.
那右上角的精灵呢？
What about the top right corner sprite?
X应该是多少？
What should the x be?
抱歉的?
Sorry?
观众：宽度
AUDIENCE: Width.
科尔顿·奥格登：是的 宽度
COLTON OGDEN: Yes, width.
一点儿没错
Exactly.
Y是多少？
What's the y?
仍然是1
Still going to be 1.
左下角呢？
What about the bottom left?
宽度、逗号高度
Width, comma height.
然后是右下角？
And then the bottom right?
观众：但这是[INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: But it's [INAUDIBLE]
科尔顿·奥格登：对不起 左下角应该是1 逗号高度
COLTON OGDEN: Sorry, bottom left should be 1, comma height.
右下角应为宽度、高度
Bottom right should be width, height.
所以基本上是检查每一块瓷砖的位置
And so basically checking the position of each tile
是我们如何推断它的ID 这就是我们在源代码中所做的
is how we can infer its ID, which is what we're doing in the source code
这里
here.
如果x是1 y是1 好的 左上角
If x is 1 and y is 1, OK, top left corner.
注意 我们已经将它们放入常量中
And notice that we've put these into constants,
我们放在常量.lua中 只是为了可读性
that we've put in the constant.lua, just for readability.
所以我们可以立即看到OK 我应该将ID磁贴设置在左上方
So we can instantly see OK, I should set ID tile top left
角 而不是某个任意的数字 这是我们对瓷砖的索引
corner, not some arbitrary number that's our index into the tile sheet.
大概40多岁 或者其他什么年龄
At maybe like 40 something, or whatever it is.
左下角是1和高度
Bottom left is 1 and height.
右上角是宽度和1 然后右下角是宽度和高度
Top right is width and 1, and then bottom right is width and height.
我们可以看到 它是可读的
And we can see, it's readable.
我们可以一目了然地看到我们在做什么 你有条件地在哪里
We can sort of see at a glance what we're doing, where you're conditionally
生成我们所有的瓷砖
generating all of our tiles.
如果这些都不是真的 那么x是1 那么这个瓦片是什么？
If none of those are true, and then x is 1, what's that tile?
如果x是1 但它不是一个角？
If x is 1, but it's not a corner?
这是一面左手边的墙
It's a left hand wall.
同样的事情是 如果它是宽度 它就是右手边的墙
And the same thing is if it's the width, it's a right hand wall.
如果y是1 它就是一面墙
And if y is 1, it's a top wall.
如果y是高度 那么它就是底部的墙
If y is height, it's a bottom wall.
如果不是这些 那就一定是一层楼
And then if it's none of those, it's got to be a floor, exactly.
所以这基本上就是我们如何产生整体的--
So that's basically how we generate the overall--
这是一个非常简单的生成算法
it's a very easy, simple generation algorithm.
我在这里所做的是随机化
What I've done is for randomization here,
我们实际上有一张桌子 上面有潜在的左墙 潜在的右墙
we have actually a table of potential left walls, potential right walls,
潜在的顶部和底部
potential top and bottom.
然后我们只需在其中指定一个随机值
And then we just ascribe it a random value within there,
基于它的规模有多大
based on however large that is.
这给了我们变量 我们可以看到它
And that gives us variable, we can see it.
我们有随机性--每次我产生它
We have random-- every time I generate it.
所以请注意视觉上的一些瓷砖
So take note of maybe some of the tiles visually
你可以在地图上看到
that you can see there on the map.
请注意 它们会发生变化
Notice that they change.
请注意 交换机也已更改
Notice that the switch has also changed.
请注意 它们再次更改
Notice that they changed again.
因此 一切都是可变的
So everything is variable.
我们有一点视觉上的多样性
We have a little bit of visual variety.
基本上 这就是我们对马里奥所做的
This is what we did, essentially, with Mario.
我们换了瓷砖套装和顶层套装
We changed the tile set, and the topper set.
只是现在我们只是在改变 我们只有一张瓷砖
Only now we're just changing, we have only one tile sheet,
但在同一块瓷砖上有几种不同的变化
but several variations at the same tile they're in.
所以我们所要做的就是随机选择任何瓷砖的变体
So all we need to do is pick a random variation of whatever tile.
这涉及到我们查看精灵薄片
And that involves us looking at the sprite sheet,
挑选出哪些单独的瓷砖 哪些瓷砖分开
picking out which individual tiles, which separate tiles,
映射到特定类型的切片 然后只需选取一个随机值
map to the specific type of tile, and then just picking a random value
从那张桌子上
from that table
这就是它的工作原理
That's how that works.
所以 我认为 有几件事需要向亲人展示
So a couple of things, I think, left to show relative
敬地牢一代
to the dungeon generation.
因此 我们已经生成了48个实体
So 48, we have generate entities.
因此 实体在这里
So entities are here.
我们知道他们的名字 对吧？
We have their names, right?
我们看到的一些实体 骷髅 蝙蝠 粘液 鬼魂 蜘蛛
Some of the entities we saw, skeletons, bats, slimes, ghosts, spiders.
这是一个非常轻量级的功能
It's a very lightweight function.
它不像15或20行 但我们正在生成
It's not like 15 or 20 lines, but we're generating
a bunch束of different不同kinds种类of entities实体.
a bunch of different kinds of entities.
因为我们所做的 我们基本上
Because what we've done, we take, we basically
从表中随机选择一种类型
take a random type from that table.
我们创建一个实体 然后使用我们所拥有的
We create an entity, and then using what we've
定义在一个叫做实体定义的全局表中
defined in a global table called Entity Defs,
我们把重要的东西
we take out what sort of matters in terms
每一个个体的产生 其特征
of generating each individual entity, the characteristics thereof,
我们把它转换成简单的数据形式
and we just put it in simple data form.
这有点像游戏的数据驱动设计
This is sort of like the segue into data driven design for your game.
如果你看这里的实体定义 我们可以看到所有的实体
If you look at Entity Defs here, we can just see that all of our entities
是一系列数据
are a sequence of data.
这里有一个参与人 在第10行.
So up here we have player, on line 10.
玩家得到一张桌子
Player gets a table.
我们给他步行速度
We give him walk speed.
我们有一个动画表
We have a table of animations.
所以他有一个向左走的动画 一个向右走的动画
So he's got a walk left animation, a walk right animation,
走下动画
a walk down animation.
所有这些都有它们的框架 它们的间隔 它们的纹理 一切
All of those have their frames, their interval, their texture, everything
就是干净的数据对吧
is just clean data, right?
这里没有逻辑 真的
There's no logic here, really.
只是一些标志 或者值 简单的东西
It's just flags, or values, simple things.
你可以给任何对我们的基本知识有一定了解的人
You could give anybody who has sort of the basic knowledge of what we're
做这个文件 也许还有一些纹理 然后说 嘿
doing this file, and maybe some textures, and say, hey,
我想让你设计
I want you to design--
我要你把所有的东西
I want you to lay out basically all of that's
参与了骨架在屏幕上的渲染
involved in what makes a skeleton render to the screen.
为他们制作所有的动画
Create all the animations for them.
给这些动画计时
Give those animations their timing.
给他们准确的框架
Give them the exact frames.
也许骨架应该有健康值 也许健康值应该等于10
Maybe skeletons should have health, and maybe health should be equal to 10
在一具骨架上 或者类似的东西上
on a skeleton, or something like that.
实际上这里没有任何编程
There's not really any programming going on here.
但我们把游戏中的一切都描述成数据
But we're describing everything in our game as data.
这在复杂的游戏中是很重要的 因为游戏系统相当复杂
And that's important thing in complex games that have fairly complex systems,
但是可以通过一些属性来建模
but that can be modeled via some attributes.
您可以只归属于实体和数据 然后让引擎解析
You can just ascribe your entities and data, and then let your engine parse
此信息 然后以编程方式创建您的实体
this information, and then create your entities programmatically.
稍微把负担从程序员转移到设计者身上
You shift the burden from the programmer to the designer, a little bit.
你请得起你的设计团队 你 也许还有其他人
And you afford your design team, you and maybe other people
对编程不太熟悉的人
who aren't as comfortable with programming,
能够修改游戏引擎 向游戏中添加内容
the ability to modify the game engine, add things to the game,
而不必查看大量的引擎代码
without having to go through the bulk of your engine code
做任何太花哨的事
and do anything too fancy.
在这种情况下 它很简单
In this case, it's simple.
我们所做的只是创建动画 并指定一个纹理
All we're doing is just we're creating animations, and assigning a texture
这些个体中的每一种
to each of these individual things.
但我上周曾暗示过这一点
But I alluded to this last week.
你可以有一个文件 它可能描述了一些类似地精的东西
You can have a file that maybe describes something like a goblin.
我们会在一堂课的最后看到这一点 它可能像一面旗帜
We'll see this at the end of a lecture, which has maybe like a flag
因为它是易燃的吗？
for is it flammable?
它的生命力有多强？
How much health does it have?
它的动画是什么？
What are its animations?
它有什么技能？
What skills does it have?
它的进攻强度有多大？
What's its attack strength?
它的辩护理由是什么？
What's its defense?
它通常在哪里产卵？
Where does it spawn typically?
通过将所有这些属性放在一起并让您的引擎进行某种解析
By putting all these attributes together and having your engine sort of parse
这个 你可以创建 取决于你有多少个字段
this, you can create, depending on how many fields you have,
你可以在你的游戏中创建非常复杂的潜在清单
you can create very complex potential list of things in your game.
无论他们是实体 无论是武器 还是物品
Whether they're entities, whether they're weapons, whether they're items,
超能力
abilities.
任何你想做的事
Anything you want to.
不管它们是不是水平
Whether they're levels, even.
仅仅基于数据
Based solely on just data.
因此 这是设计和开发的圣杯
So this is a holy grail of design and development
当你进入像RPG这样特别复杂的游戏时
when you get into especially very complex games like RPGs,
在那里你可以拥有具有粒子效果的技能
where you can have skills that have particle effects
对不同的东西造成不同的伤害
and do different damage to different things.
你有一些实体--也许你想让它们被烧毁
And you have entities that are-- maybe you want them some to set on fire,
有些人会触电身亡
some to be electrocuted.
也许有些你不知道
Maybe some you don't.
也许当他们接触到什么东西时 一些会融化
Maybe some melt when they touch something.
创建一串旗帜 创建一个函数
Create a bunch of flags, create a function
它对此进行解析 并生成结果实体
that parses this, and generates entities as a result.
你只需要让你自己的工作效率得到令人难以置信的提升
And you just allow yourself an incredible boost in productivity.
您不再需要创建蜘蛛类、幽灵类、蝙蝠类
No longer do you need to create a spider class, a ghost class, a bat class.
这都是不必要的
It's all unnecessary.
你所需要做的就是定义蝙蝠有哪些属性？
All you need to do is define what sort of attributes does a bat have?
幽灵有什么属性？
What attributes does a ghost have?
骨架有哪些属性？
What attributes does a skeleton have?
因此 任何人都可以因此修改您的游戏
And anybody can therefore mod your game as a result of this.
他们所需要做的就是知道一个潜在实体可以具有哪些属性
All they need to do is know what attributes a potential entity can have.
因此 您的设计团队的工作效率会更高
And your design team is all the more productive as a result.
所以这就是为什么这是一个相关的说辞
So that's a spiel on why this is relevant.
我们已经实现了一个非常基本的版本
We've implemented a very basic version of this
只是为了制作动画模型
just for the sake of modeling animations.
但我们不需要为游戏中的所有不同实体创建单独的类
But we don't need a separate class for all the different entities in our game
世界
world.
我们只需要 基本上 在这个游戏的背景下
We just need, basically, and in the context of this game,
他们的动画是什么？
what are their animations?
这就是实体定义 这就是它的工作方式 如果我们
So that's entity defs, that's how it's working if we're
看看第48行的room.lua
looking at room.lua at line 48.
它所做的一切就是制作动画
All its doing is getting animations.
顺便说一句 这是您的函数 它接受这些定义
This is, by the way, your function that takes in these definitions
并创建你的实体
and creates your entities.
他们应该寻找--
They should be looking for--
正在调查这件事
looking into that.
他们提取该定义 然后解析出
They pull that definition and then just parse out
每一条相关的数据
each individual relevant piece of data.
然后只需构建一些相关信息
And then just construct some relevant information
或将相关标志附加到该实体 以便您的游戏引擎稍后可以
or attach a relevant flag to that entity that your game engine can then later
解析
parse.
举个易燃的例子 如果你进行攻击 而攻击是火力类型的
The flammable example, if you do an attack and that attack is of type fire,
它与一个实体相撞 这个实体 易燃是真的
and it collides with an entity, and that entity.flammable is true,
这应该会引发一些行为
that should trigger some behavior.
但你不需要做任何非常复杂的事情
But you don't need to do anything terribly complex.
此后 您可以将其分配给任何任意实体
And you can assign this to any arbitrary entity thereafter.
所以 这只是一种简单的方法来获取游戏中非常复杂的行为
So just a simple way of getting very complex behavior for your game
对象 实体 任何你想要的东西
objects, entities, whatever you want.
将它们建模为数据 而不是从类的角度考虑
Modeling them as data rather than thinking about it in terms of classes.
就是这样
So that's that.
有没有人有任何问题 比如它是如何工作的
Does anybody have any questions just like sort of how that works,
或者为什么它是可行的？
or why it's viable?
或者为什么它有用？
Or why it's useful?
好的
OK.
最后几件事 我们会在房间里快速看一看
Couple of last things we'll look at really fast in room.
所以上网82
So online 82.
生成对象
Generate objects.
所以我们上周做了非常非常相似的事情
So we did this very, very similarly last week.
在那里我们刚刚有了一个游戏对象类
Where we just had a game object class.
请注意 它本身就是一个交换机的定义
Notice that it takes itself a definition for a switch.
这个定义在游戏对象.lua中
That definition is in gameobjects.lua.
换个位置
Switch.
这是一种更类似于开关的数据建模
Here's a little bit more sort of data modeling something like a switch.
它有一种类型的开关 默认的帧是2 所以宽度和高度都是16
It's got a type of switch, frame is 2 by default. So width and height of 16.
它并不结实
It's not solid.
玩家可以走过去
Player can walk over it.
其默认状态为抑制
Its default state is upressed.
因此 当它被催生到游戏中时 它是不受压力的
So when it gets spawned into the game, it's unpressed.
它有两种潜在的状态 史无前例的和紧迫的
And it's got two potential states, unprecedented and pressed.
这些州中的每一个都有一个框架
And each of those states have a frame.
所以我们要做的就是呈现它 它的当前状态是什么？
So all we need to do to render it is say, what's its current state?
呈现此状态 帧
Render this state.frame.
然后现在 我们不需要做任何事情--
And then now, we don't need to do anything--
这基本上就是我们所需要做的 以便在正确的点上呈现它
that's basically all we need to do in order to render it at the right point.
因此 您的游戏引擎需要查看对象
Your game engine, therefore, needs to look at your object,
并查看其状态和潜在状态 索引到该状态
and look at its state and look at its potential states, index into that state
然后从那里拉出框架
and then pull the frame from that.
但它为你提供了一种无限的灵活性
But it forwards you sort of infinite flexibility.
你现在可以有一个发光的状态
You can now have maybe of a glowing state,
也许在那张精灵纸上有一个框架让它发光
and maybe there's a frame in that sprite sheet that allows it to glow.
你可以随时随地把它换成发光
And you could just change it to glowing whenever you want,
它会恰到好处地渲染
and it'll just render appropriately.
所以对数据建模的方法非常灵活
So very flexible approach to modeling data.
房间有149个房间
149 in room.
所以我们快完成这里的地牢了
So we're almost done with the dungeon here.
所以149是我们的更新功能
So 149 is our update function.
它所做的基本上就是遍历所有内容
All it does basically is iterate through everything
并更新它 基本上包括所有实体
and update it, including basically all the entities.
所以对于每个实体来说 如果它的生命值小于或等于0 它就是死的
So for every entity if its health is less than or equal to 0, it's dead.
如果它是死的 那么不要渲染它 我们在渲染中看到了这一点
If it's dead, then don't render it, which we see down in render.
但如果它没有死 而且玩家自己撞到了它
But if it's not dead, and self.player player collides with it,
而且玩家并不脆弱 那么我们就应该伤害玩家
and the player's not vulnerable, then we should damage the player,
变得无懈可击
go invulnerable.
如果玩家的健康状况为零 则切换到游戏结束
And if the player's health is zero, change to game over.
所以请注意这是多么的可读性
So notice how readable this is.
当您也像这样对实体建模时 您真正需要做的就是
When you model your entities like this as well, all you really need to do
只是检查某些标志或函数
is just check for certain flags or functions,
你可以像这样做任意复杂的测试
and you can do arbitrarily complex tests like this.
因为实体可能是死的 也可能不是
Because entities can be dead, or not.
因为实体可以是无懈可击的 也可以不是
Because entities can be invulnerable, or not.
然后因为实体都是XY的 在我们的游戏中基于高度的东西
And then because entities are all xy, with height based things in our game,
而碰撞只是希望他们拥有这一点
and collide just expects them to have that.
我们所做的只是播放声音 伤害玩家
All we just do is play sound, damage the player.
伤害在即刻会造成什么影响？
What does damage do offhand?
你觉得它能做什么？
What do you think it does?
观众：我会胡乱猜测 然后说减去你的健康
AUDIENCE: I'll take a wild guess and say subtracts from your health.
科尔顿·奥格登：没错
COLTON OGDEN: Exactly.
随便猜一猜 就会说它有损健康
Just take a wild guess and say it subtracts from health.
确实如此
It does.
所以实体伤害只是一个数字 然后从生命值中减去这个数字
So entity damage just takes in a number, and subtracts that from health.
这就是它的全部功能
That's all it does.
变得无懈可击
Go invulnerable.
那是做什么的
What does that do.
观众：这意味着你已经遭受了那么多秒的伤害？
AUDIENCE: Means you've been taking damage for that many seconds?
科尔顿·奥格登：的确如此
COLTON OGDEN: It does.
它可以防止你在那么长的时间内受到伤害
It prevents you from taking damage for that many seconds.
所有这些实际上只是设置了一个标志 我已经提到了很多
All that really does is just set a flag, which I've alluded to quite a bit
已经是一个任意的标志 您可以通过数据或其他方式进行建模
already, an arbitrary flag that you can model via data or some other means.
每个实体都有一面坚不可摧的旗帜
Every entity has an invulnerable flag.
如果它是无懈可击的 那么引擎应该寻找它
And if it's invulnerable, then the engine should look for that,
并相应地更改渲染和实体的机制
and change the rendering, and the mechanics of the entity accordingly.
最后这里 很简单 如果玩家的健康等于0
And then lastly here, just simple if the player health is equal to 0,
这可能是在我们受到足够的伤害后 更改为游戏结束
which it might be after we take sufficient damage, change to Game Over.
这就是它的全部功能
That's all it does.
然后 对于每个对象 就像我们对每个实体所做的那样 更新对象
And then for every object, just as we do with every entity, update the object
如果玩家与其相撞 则触发其碰撞功能
and if the player collides with it, then trigger its On Collide function.
这可以是你任意创建的函数
And this can be a function that you arbitrarily create,
取决于您的对象的需求
depending on the needs of your object.
例如 如果你抬头看这里 每次我们创建一个房间
If you look up here, for example, every time we create a room,
我们在房间里生成对象
we generate objects in the room.
我们在对象中插入了一个开关 这是我们在前面看到的 在gameobjects.lua中
We insert into objects a switch, which we saw before, in gameobjects.lua.
取x和y
And takes an x and a y.
在这种情况下 我们只需确保x和y
In this case, we just make sure that the x and y
是地图左上角之间的一个随机数
is a random number between the top left of the map
和地图的右下角 在它所具有的填充内
and the bottom right of the map, within the padding that it has.
我们得到了对该对象的引用
We get a reference to that object.
然后定义了Are on Collide函数
And then we define are On Collide function.
所以我们要做的就是说如果它被压制了
So what we do is we say if it's upressed,
回想一下 我们在游戏对象定义中有一个状态
so recall that we have a state in the game object definition.
如果是未熨烫的 就改成熨烫
If it's unpressed, change it to pressed.
这就是我们真正需要做的
It's all we really need to do.
然后注意这里 比如k 有一扇门
And then notice here, for k, a doorway.
因此 对于每一扇门 无论是自己的门 都要把门敞开
So for every doorway in doorways, self.doorways, set that doorway open
是真的
is true.
然后播放一声门声
And then play a door sound.
所以我们的On Collide函数只是相互作用
So our On Collide function just interacts
与游戏世界中的其他东西 以及非常简单的东西
with other things in the game world, and just very simple things
但有一种非常有趣的机械师
but has a pretty interesting sort of mechanic.
就像我们有一个...
Like we have a--
我从蝙蝠那里得到了伤害 因为我的产卵并不完美
I took damage off the bat there, because my spawning isn't perfect.
但它从--请注意 它的状态从未按下更改
But it changed from-- notice that it changed its state from unpressed
按下
to pressed.
因为它从唯一的精灵变成了--
Because it went from the one sprite to--
我去另一个房间 这样我们就能看到了
I'll go into another room so we can see that.
我会在路上弄坏一些东西
I'll take some damage on the way.
去另一个房间
Go to another room.
请注意精灵
Notice the sprite.
它看起来像是没有被压住的 对吗？
It sort of looks like it's unpressed, right?
因为游戏对象的默认状态是未按下的
Because the game object's default state is unpressed.
然后当我在它上面的时候就会触发碰撞
And then On Collide triggers when I go on top of it.
它会更改状态 这会对渲染的内容产生影响
It changes state, which has an effect on what gets rendered.
它是关于Collide函数的调用 该函数
And it's On Collide function is called, which
把房间的每一扇门都打开了
opened up every doorway in the room.
如此简单 就像15行代码
So simple like 15 lines of code.
但为了我们的地牢 我们的行为很吸引人 很有趣
But pretty compelling, interesting behavior for the sake of our dungeon.
就像 它增加了很多东西 就这么简单
Like, it adds a lot, as simple as that is.
现在我们感觉就像是在互动
Now we sort of feel like we're interacting
和我们的游戏世界有一点关系
with our game world a little bit.
这就是它的工作原理
So that's how that works.
最后 在第188行上进行渲染
And then lastly, rendering on line 188.
只需检查我们所有的瓷砖 渲染所有瓷砖
Just go through all of our tiles, render all the tiles.
我们以前见过这种情况
We've seen this before.
渲染所有的门口 渲染所有的物体
Render all the doorways, render all the objects,
渲染所有实体 如果它们没有死的话
render all the entities, if they're not dead.
对吗？
Right?
如果它们已经死了 那么就不要渲染它们
If they're dead, then don't render them.
然后这一点 我们将看看结尾 这是模版
And then this bit here, we'll take a look at the end, which is stenciling.
所以请注意当我走进门的时候
So notice that when I walk through doors.
首先 请注意 如果门是关着的 我是不能走进去的
Well first of all, notice that I can't walk through doors if they're closed,
这一点很重要
which is important.
因此 当你与门口的物体碰撞时 如果Doorway.Open为False
So when you collide with your doorway objects, if doorway.Open is false,
它不应该触发房间开关 对吗？
it shouldn't trigger the room switch, right?
但如果我打开门 它们现在都会被召回
But if I open the doors they're now all set to recall.
Door.open现在等于True
Door.open is now equal to true.
所以他们改变了他们的渲染 现在他们正在渲染开放的门口
So they've changed their renderings, and now they're rendering open doorways.
如果我穿过它 注意到它看起来像是玩家走的
If I walk through it, notice that it looks as if the player walks
在瓷砖下面
underneath the tiles.
但我是在玩家面前画牌
But I'm drawing the tiles before the player.
还有一种你可能认为应该做的方法
And one approach that you might think to do
当创造出这种令人信服的行走外观时
when sort of creating this believable appearance of walking
穿过一扇门 就是说好
through a doorway, is say OK.
我只会在渲染之后渲染播放器 然后再渲染门口
I'll just render the player after I render before I render the doorways.
对吗？
Right?
所以最后渲染所有的门
So render all the doorways last.
但这并不是很有效 因为精灵实际上就是从这里开始的
But it doesn't quite work out, because the sprite actually starts right here.
所以有人会认为如果我是
So what does somebody think is going to happen if I were
在玩家身后画门口吗？
to draw the doorway after the player?
观众：如果你越过这条线或[INAUDIBLE] 你的默认玩家就会消失
AUDIENCE: Your default player disappears if you cross that line or [INAUDIBLE]
越过那条线
over that line.
科尔顿·奥格登：没错
COLTON OGDEN: Exactly.
球员一走到这一小段线就会消失
The player would disappear as soon as he gets to this little bit of line right
在这里 这不是很有说服力
here, which is not very convincing.
实际上 我现在就试着去掉模版
And actually I'll try right now to take away the stenciling,
这样我们就能看到那是什么样子了
so we can see what that looks like.
所以如果我去掉这里的模板 然后我只需要渲染
So if I just take away the stenciling here, and then I just render.
今天不能打字
Can't type today.
所以我要继续了
So I'm going to go ahead.
那就去吧
Do that.
首先 渲染顺序是这样的 现在门口渲染
Well, first of all, the rendering order is such that now the doorways render
在球员之前
after before the player.
所以他就直接从他们身上走过去 对吗？
So he just walks right over them, right?
所以我只是在走 我是在跨过墙
So I'm just walking, I was walking over the walls.
这并不令人信服
That's not compelling.
如果我要做一些简单的事情 比如改变渲染顺序
And if I were to do something as simple as change the rendering order.
因此 现在 门口首先进行渲染
So right now, the doorways render first.
我将在玩家之后渲染门口
I'll just render the doorways after the player.
所以就在这里 我把它拿出来了 对吗？
So right here, I took that out, right?
不是的
No.
所以现在 他们在玩家面前进行渲染
So right now, they render before the player.
我想按照玩家的名字来渲染它们
I want to render them after the player.
我要把它运行起来
And I'm going to just run it.
然后踩下开关
And then going to step on the switch.
然后 是的
And then, yep.
请注意 我们也会遇到一些奇怪的行为
Notice we get some weird behavior, too.
就像看到他的头被砍掉一样？
Like sees his head is getting cut off?
以及其他实体也是如此 对吗？
And other entities as well, right?
在这种情况下 我真的看不出来
In that case, I couldn't really tell.
不过 是的
But yeah.
非常奇怪的撕裂行为
Very weird rending behavior.
我们要做的就是创造一种被称为模板的东西
And what we do to fix that is we create what's called a stencil.
因此 基本上我会尝试获得一个屏幕截图 我可以在这里展示
So basically I'll try and get a screenshot here I can show.
首先 让我修改一下我刚才所做的更改
First let me fix the changes that I just made.
正确的
Right.
然后如果我回到这里的代码
And then if I go back into the code here.
所以模板只是--我们稍后会看到一张幻灯片
So a stencil is just-- and we'll see a slide on this in a little bit.
但模板基本上是任何类型的任意形状
But a stencil is just basically any sort of arbitrary shape that want,
你画在屏幕上的
that you draw onto the screen.
它是看不见的 但它决定了
It's invisible, but it determines whatever
在该模板上绘制 它确定是否
gets drawn on top of that stencil, it determines whether or not
那东西就会被渲染
that thing gets rendered.
所以我有一个模板 基本上是从这里一直到下一个房间
So I have a stencil going basically from here onwards to the next room.
所以就在门口撞到拱门的地方
So right about where the doorway hits the archway,
因为这就是我们想要玩家的头
because that's where we want the player's head
让它看起来像是消失了
to look like it disappears.
模板放在这里
Stencil going here.
我这里有一支钢笔
I have a stencil going right here.
就在这里
And right here.
在右边也是如此
And on the right side as well.
这样做的目的是我已经设置了模板
And what that does is I've set the stencil
说出在分类过程中通过这个模板的任何东西
to say whatever passes through this stencil during the sort
模板测试期 我们所做的只是
of stencil testing period which is, well all we do is we just
在这段时间内画出玩家
draw the player during that time.
但基本上 如果它在模板上 就不会呈现它
But basically if it's on the stencil, don't render it.
所以它的影响是我们仍然
And so it what that has the effect of is we still
在玩家面前画出门道
draw the doorways before the player.
所以球员走进来 他被拉到了这一部分的上方
So the player walks in and he's drawn above this part.
但一旦他打到模板 他就没有被画出来
But as soon as he hits the stencil, he's not drawn.
它只是--所有这些 基本上它所做的
It just-- all those, basically what it does
它将字符绘制到模具上 而不是实际的画布上
is it draws the character to the stencil, and not to the actual canvas.
因此 如果你想要令人信服的分层、怪异的视觉效果
And so we get if you want convincing layered, weird, visual effects
就像这样 模版是一种方法
like that, stenciling is an approach.
好的
OK.
然后就是这一切
And then that's all this.
所以这个模板函数 love.graph 模板
So this stencil function, love.graphics.stencil,
接受一个函数
takes in a function.
这是在实际的模版过程中要运行的内容
This is what's going to run during the actual stenciling process.
它将会抽签--
It's going to draw--
我画了四个矩形
I draw four rectangles.
所有那些矩形就是那些拱门
All those rectangles are just those archways.
对吗？
Right?
完美地覆盖在它们上面 这样它就可以进入隔壁的房间
Perfectly layered over them such that it goes into the next room.
然后我们就这么做了
And then we do.
请注意 它显示的是替换 然后是1
Notice that it says Replace, and then 1.
因此 我们替换绘制到该模板上的任何像素
So we replace any pixel that gets drawn to that stencil
模板值为1
with the stencil value of 1.
然后我们只在模具测试中画小于1的东西
And then we only draw things that are less than 1 during the stencil test.
这意味着任何没有被归因于值1的东西
Which means anything that didn't get ascribed to value of 1, which
也就是说 如果玩家翻阅了模板
means that if the player went over the stencil,
得到的像素值为1 则为假
got a pixel value of 1, that's going to be false.
他不会被屏幕所吸引
He's not going to be drawn to the screen.
是?
Yes?
观众：所以你是在刻版 如果你创造了一个不同的形状
AUDIENCE: So you are stenciling, if you created a different shape,
你可以利用这一点 比如说 像灯光系统一样 一些区域是黑暗的
you could use that, for say, like a light system, some areas are dark,
有些区域是亮的吗？
some areas are light?
科尔顿·奥格登：很好的问题是 如果你有一个模板 因为你
COLTON OGDEN: Good question was if you have a stencil, because you
可以使用任意形状 您可以
can do with an arbitrary shape, you could
在某些区域为暗区域 而某些区域为亮区域的情况下创建照明系统
create lighting systems where some areas are dark, and some areas are light.
我想说有可能
I want to say possibly.
问题是 我不能100%确定模板是否允许你这样做
The thing is, I'm not 100% sure whether stenciling allows you to do,
爱2D模板是否允许你做任意的数字
whether love 2D stenciling allows you to do arbitrary numbers.
我基本上不确定它是开着还是关着 还是渐变
I basically am not sure if it's on or off, or a gradient.
通常 如果我这样做我们的照明系统
Typically, if I were to do our lighting system like that,
我可能会画一个假的照明系统
I would probably draw a faux lighting system.
第一 你可以使用照明套件 比如盒子
One, you can use a lighting kit, like box
2D灯光 这对你来说真的很吸引人 很酷的灯光
2D lights, which does really compelling, cool lights for you.
或者是一种更粗鲁的方式 但也可能是现实的
Or sort of a cruder way to do it, but possibly realistic,
就是画一个形状 适合你想要成为黑暗的任何东西
would be to draw a shape that fits whatever you want to be your darkness,
然后以低于100%的不透明度进行渲染
and then render it at an opacity that's less than 100%.
所以你会有一个房间 比方说可能在它的两边
So you'd have a room, and let's say maybe to sides of it
都有些模糊
are kind of shadowy.
你在那里画黑色的矩形 对吗？
You draw black rectangles there, right?
但是 这些黑色矩形不是以255阿尔法绘制的
But instead of drawing those black rectangles at 255 alpha,
你把它们画在200或150 或者类似的地方
you draw them at 200 or 150, or something like that.
所以你仍然可以看到它们下面是什么
And so you can still see what's underneath them,
但看起来它们似乎是一个影子
but it looks as if they are a shadow.
你可以使用渐变效果来做同样的事情
And you can use gradient effects to do the same thing.
如果你想要更深更浅的阴影
If you want to have shadow that's darker going lighter,
我相信你可以在Love 2D中画出带有渐变效果的矩形
I believe you can draw rectangles with a gradient effect in Love 2D.
我还得再深入调查一下
I'd have to look into a little bit more.
但你会想要做这样的事
But you would look to do something like that.
通过某个矩形或任意形状绘制阴影的渐变
Draw a gradient of shadow via some rectangle, or some arbitrary shape,
在这种情况下模拟照明
to simulate lighting in that case.
你可以完成类似的事情
And you could accomplish something similar to that.
还有很多其他疯狂的很酷的方式 我在2D中看到过闪电
And there are a lot of other crazy cool ways I've seeing lightning done in 2D.
但这可能是我能想到的最简单的方法了
But that's probably offhand the simplest way that I could think of doing it.
凉爽的
Cool.
所以这就是模版 基本上就是这样
So that's stenciling, and that's basically it
对于地牢一代来说 这可以说是最重要的部分
for the dungeon generation, which is arguably the most important part.
我们之前也看过这种过渡机制
And also we looked earlier at the sort of transition mechanic.
我们将更多地了解过渡机械师
And we'll look at the transition mechanic a little bit more
稍等片刻
in a little bit.
但让我们现在花五分钟 然后回到那个问题上
But let's take a five minute for right now, and then come back to that
再看看更多的东西
and see some more stuff.
好的
All right.
欢迎回到第五讲 塞尔达传奇
Welcome back to Lecture 5, Legend of Zelda.
所以在休息之前 我们谈到了一些
So before the break, we talked about a bunch
在不同的事物中 地牢一代是其中最重要的
of different things, dungeon generation being foremost among them.
现在我们将真正开始谈论像Hitbox和Hurtbox这样的东西
Now we'll actually start talking about things like hitboxes and hurtboxes,
正如我们在屏幕上看到的那样
as we can see here on the screen.
因此 Hitbox基本上是一个长方形
So a hitbox is a rectangle, basically.
这就是我们在发行版中实现它的方式
And it's how we've implemented it in the distro.
但我们在这里可以看到有几种不同的
But we can see here there's a few different sort
矩形重叠的部分
of rectangles overlapping.
我们这里有绿色的长方形
We have the green rectangles here.
这些都是伤害箱
These are hurtboxes.
这就是你可能受伤的地方
These are where you can get hurt.
然后这是一个Hitbox
And then this is a hitbox.
这是你可以击球的地方
This is where you can hit something.
所以游戏 特别是格斗游戏
And so games, like especially with fighting games,
在许多相当复杂的互动游戏中
in a lot of games of fairly complex interactions,
以及拥有武器或粒子的复杂实体
and complex entities that have weapons or particles,
诸如此类的事情都会造成损害
things like that all do damage.
你会看到很多复杂的重叠
You'll see a lot of complicated overlapping,
以及这些矩形的排列 这就带来了
and arrangement of these rectangles that sort of bring about
物体如何在碰撞方面相互作用
how things interact with each other in terms of collision,
造成损害 并影响到其他实体
and doing damage, and affecting other entities.
在这种情况下 他正在进行从左到右的攻击
In this case, he's doing an attack that goes from the left to the right.
这是一次低位进攻
It's a low attack.
只是他的脚 从本质上讲 有点向内
Only his foot, essentially, a little bit inwards.
但从本质上说 他的脚是有损伤的 而他的其余部分是脆弱的
But essentially his foot does damage, whereas the rest of him is vulnerable.
如果有人从上面走到他跟前攻击他
If someone were to come up to him from up above and attack him,
这会造成一些损害
it would do some damage.
还有《我的世界》 它向你展示了同样的原则
And there's Minecraft, and it shows you how the same sort of principle
同样适用于3D游戏
applies to 3D games as well.
在这种情况下 你看到的都是伤害箱
In this case, what you see there are all hurtboxes.
这些人都意识到事情可能会受到伤害
Those are all aware things can get hurt.
尽管这些东西很少是物品
Even though those are few of those things are items,
因此 这只会真正影响玩家是否与它们相撞
so that only really affects whether or not the player collides with them
然后把它们捡起来
and picks them up.
但这基本上就是Hitbox和Hurtbox之间的区别
But that's basically the difference between hitboxes and hurtboxes.
我想我不小心把这个文件命名为hurtbox的发行版
The distro I think I accidentally called the file hurtbox.
所以当我把它往上推时 它会被重新命名为Hitbox
So when I push it up, it's going to be renamed hitbox,
因为这就是我们使用它的目的
because that's what we use it for.
但在这场比赛中有什么是即兴的 我们需要Hitbox做什么？
But what is offhand in this game, what do we need a hitbox for?
观众：[听不见]呼啸而来的攻击
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] attacks from the swoord.
科尔顿·奥格登：用剑攻击
COLTON OGDEN: Attacks with a sword.
我们需要Hitbox的原因是什么？
And the reason that we need a hitbox for that is why?
观众：致[INAUDIBLE]大热
AUDIENCE: To [INAUDIBLE] the hit.
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yes.
为什么我们不能只使用球员的位置x-y宽度和高度？
And why can't we just use the player's position x-y width and height?
观众：因为它也有一个方向
AUDIENCE: Because it has a direction as well.
科尔顿·奥格登：因为它也有方向 也需要--
COLTON OGDEN: Because it has a direction as well, and also it needs--
这基本上就是它的伤害性武器
that's essentially its hurtbox.
对吗？
Right?
所以这两个原因
So those two reasons.
它有我们需要作为它参考点的方向
It has that direction that we need to sort of act as its reference point
用于生成命中框 对其他实体造成伤害
for generating a hit box, to inflict damage on other entities.
我们需要使用玩家的主Hitbox
And we need to use the player's main hitbox
以及伤害盒 它已经必须看看是否有什么东西
and hurtbox that it already has to see if something
击球 球员 也许是从另一边 或者类似的东西
hit it, the player, maybe from another side, or something like that.
那么 让我们继续下去 看看这里
So let's go ahead and take a look here.
处理Hitbox的主要代码 在本例中
The main bit of code that deals with the hitbox, in this case,
其中一个将会成为伤害盒
is one going to be hurtbox.
应该是希特波斯
Should be hitbox.
但我们可以看到 这实际上只是一个矩形类
But we can see this is literally just a rectangle class.
XY 宽度和高度
xy, a width and a height.
自学 自学
self.x, self.y, self-taught, self.width, self.height equals all those things.
这就是你对Hitbox所需要的一切
That's all you need for a hitbox.
字面意思就是盒子 你所需要的就是那些字段
Literally box, just all you need are those fields.
然后你可以做简单的碰撞
And then you can do simply collides.
就像你做实体一样
Just like you do entity.
实体碰撞伤害箱
Entity collides hurtbox.
是 不 对或错
Yes, no, true or false.
因为回想起来 碰撞预期XY宽度或高度
Because recall, collides expects xy width or height.
它定义了一个整体Lua
And it's defined an entity.lua.
因此 如果我们上升到玩家状态
So if we go up to the player states.
回想一下 上周我们介绍了这个想法
So recall, last week we introduced the idea
让玩家维护自己的状态集合
of having the player maintain its own collection of states,
在状态机中
in a state machine.
而不仅仅是游戏世界有一个状态机
As opposed to just the game world having a state machine that
影响我们是否在开始屏幕上
influences whether we're at the Start screen,
Play State屏幕 无论我们想要将游戏划分成什么
the Play State screen, whatever we want to divide our game up into.
我们也有实体国家
We have entities states as well.
其中之一是--所以我们在行走状态下有空闲的
Now one of those is the-- so we have the idle in the walk state.
这些与上周的非常相似 空闲状态 他们是
Those are so very similar to last week's, where the idle state, they're
只是站着不动
just standing still.
以及它们正在移动的行走状态 它们的动画也会相应地改变
And the walking state they're moving and their animation changes accordingly.
摆剑状态是一个新的状态 而这个状态的作用是
The swing sword state is a new state, and what this does
是玩家按空格键
is the player presses spacebar.
它会触发这种摇摆的剑状态
It triggers this swing sword state.
有一部新的动画
There's a new animation.
因此 我们进入摆动剑动画 相对于我们所处的方向
So we go into the swing sword animation, relative to which direction we're in.
我们得到那个方向 然后我们计算xy的宽度和高度
And we get that direction and then we calculate the xy width and height
不管我们的伤害箱是什么
of whatever our hurtbox.
应该是Hitbox 是要换剑的
Should be hitbox, is going to be for the sword.
当剑射中某物时
When the sword hits something.
所以Hitbox 如果它朝向左边 它是
So that hitbox, if it's facing the left, it's
将是8像素宽乘16高 这
going to be 8 pixels wide by 16 tall, which
大致在球员的左侧
is roughly the left side of the player.
然后我们只计算x和y 取决于我们所处的位置
And then we just calculate the x and y depending on which position we're in.
它应该大致居中 基于球员的方向
It should be roughly centered based on whatever direction the player is
看着
looking at.
然后我们在这里实例化这个伤害框
And so we then instantiate that hurtbox here.
我们管它叫自助式剑术保镖
We call it a self.swordhurtbox.
然后我们真正需要做的是什么？
And then all we really need to do is what?
在我们的游戏循环中检查我们是否击中了实体？
In our game loop to check to see if we've hit an entity?
我们只需要循环我们房间中的实体 当前房间 对吗？
We just need to loop over the entities in our room, the current room right?
这里
Here.
所以地牢当前房间里的每一个实体 实体
So every entity in the dungeon's current room.entities.
如果实体与我们的利剑伤害箱、利剑希特箱相撞
If the entity collides with our sword hurtbox, sword hitbox,
然后 我们以前见过这种方法 实体破坏一次
then, we saw this method before, entity damage one.
然后击打敌人的游戏
And then hit enemy play.
事情就是这么简单
That's as simple as it is.
回想一下 在房间里 Lua 如果一个实体的生命值降到1以下 降到0
And recall, in room.Lua, if an entity's health dropped below one, dropped to 0,
它只会触发它变得死亡
it would just trigger it to become dead.
对吗？
Right?
这就是我们有效地需要的一切
And so that's all we need effectively.
然后我们有一些额外的逻辑来确保
And then we have some additional logic to make sure
动画只播放一次
that the animation only plays one time.
然后 一旦它播放了一次 将其状态更改为空闲
And then once it has played one time, change its state to idle.
然后我们可以在相同的状态下重复按空格键
And then we can press spacebar repeatedly within that same state,
如果我们想的话就继续摇摆
just to keep swinging if we want to.
它将重新启动动画 然后重新启动
And it will just restart the animation, and restart
正在实例化的Hitbox
the hitbox being instantiated.
这就是我们真正需要做的一切
And so that's all we really need to do for that.
现在我在挥剑的底部有几行代码
Now I have some lines of code here at the bottom of the sword swing
国家 卢阿
state.lua.
和选手佩剑 摆剑状态
And player swords, swings swords state.
而它们所做的是有时它是有用的
And what these do is sometimes it's useful
当你编程来查看你的碰撞框在哪里时 对吗？
when you're programming to sort of see where your collision boxes are, right?
因为你不一定知道一切是否都完美地排列在一起
Because you don't necessarily know if everything's lined up perfectly.
当您检测不同实体之间的冲突时
When you're detecting collision between different entities,
您只需要检查一下这些矩形是否确实重叠
you want to just check to see are the rectangles actually overlapping
这是什么时候触发的？
when this triggers?
所以你所需要做的就是一目了然地看到它
So all you need to do in order to visually see this at a glance,
你可能以前在其他游戏或调试模式的游戏中见过这种情况
and you may have seen this before, in other games or debug modes of games,
就是画一条长方形的线
is just draw a line rectangles.
然后给他们你想看的XY宽度和高度 对吗？
And then just give them the xy width and height that you want to look at, right?
所以 在这里 我将继续并保存这个
So here, I'm going to go ahead and save this.
然后我要运行--
And then I'm going to run the--
我基本上没有评论过它
I've basically uncommented it.
因为默认情况下 我不想让它显示出来
Because by default, I don't want it showing.
它们是粉红色的矩形 我不想让它们显示在屏幕上
They're pink rectangles, I don't want them displayed on screen,
除非我想做调试
unless I want to do debugging.
因此 我将在这里取消对它们的注释
So I'm going to uncomment them down here.
请注意 它将颜色设置为255 0 255
Notice it sets the color to 255, 0 255.
那是洋红色
That's magenta.
我来负责这件事
I'm going to run this.
[音乐播放]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
把音量调小一点
Turn that down a little bit.
看起来没有什么特别的不同
Nothing looks particularly different.
但当我挥动我的剑时 注意到有一个小矩形
But when I swing my sword, notice that there's a little rectangle.
长方形也不一定是100%完美的
And the rectangles aren't 100% perfect necessarily.
他们给了球员一点优势
They give the player little bit of an advantage.
就像上面一样 就像他的Hitbox几乎什么都不是
Like up above, like his hitbox is barely anything.
在上面 在实际动画中 但在碰撞中
Up above, in the actual animation, but in the collision,
我对它敬而远之
I give it quite a wide berth.
所以这就是为什么你可以 在某种程度上
And so that's how you can, at a glance, sort of
看看你的东西是否有适当的相互作用
see whether your things are interacting appropriately.
有几行代码
There's lines of code.
我为其他州做了同样的事情 实体 步行
I did the same thing for the other states, the entity, walking,
和空闲状态
and idle states.
如果你想看看这些 不仅能看到球员
If you want to sort of look at those, and see not only the player
挥舞着剑 还有其他实体 以及他们的碰撞框
swinging the sword, but also the other entities, and the collision boxes they
有 只是为了检查它们是否适当地重叠
have, and just to check whether or not they're overlapping appropriately,
或者改变它们 或者随心所欲地处理它们
or to change them, or do whatever you want with them.
但这是一种很好的方式--
But that's a nice way to do--
有时很难调试冲突 如果您
sometimes it's hard to debug collision if you
我看不清到底是怎么回事
can't see exactly what's going on.
因为它通常只是XY的宽度和高度 等等
Because it's often just in terms of xy width and height, so on and so forth,
有偏移量之类的
with offsets and such.
这可能是一种痛苦和/或一种困难
It can be kind of a pain and/or sort of difficult
以这种方式追踪特定的虫子
to track down certain bugs that way.
所以只要画到屏幕上就行了
So just draw to the screen.
你可以将同样的逻辑应用到你的游戏世界中的许多事情上
You can apply that same logic to a lot of things in your game world
这可能是隐藏的 但您希望看到某种视觉上的只是绘制形状
that may be hidden, but you want to see sort of visually just draw shapes
或者为他们画不同的东西
or draw different things for them.
这样你就能看到发生了什么
So you can see what's going on.
对于我们的球员来说 这就是Hitbox和Hurtbox的工作方式
So that's how the hitbox and hurtbox work for our player.
你可以很容易地为其他实体产生更多的点击率
And you can easily just spawn more hitboxes for other entities
如果你想的话
if you want to.
如果你想给他们州 或者
If you wanted to give them states, or maybe
你想制造具有攻击性的投射物
you want to create projectiles that are offensive.
也许只是制造炮弹 然后发射炮弹
Maybe just create projectiles, and then shoot projectiles
在特定方向上 但将Hitbox分配给该射弹
in a specific direction, but assign a hitbox to that projectile,
如果你想的话
if you want to.
或者只使用XY宽度和高度投射物
Or just use the projectiles xy width and height,
然后你就可以这样计算碰撞了
and then you can calculate a collision that way.
只需将其视为游戏对象或实体即可
Just treat it like a game object, or an entity.
由你决定
It's up to you.
或者一起上一个单独的班级
Or a separate class all together.
但简而言之 这就是打击手和伤害者
But that's hitboxes and hurtboxes in a nutshell.
有没有人对这些工作原理有任何疑问？
Anybody have any questions as to how those sort of work?
好的 酷
OK, cool.
那么 让我们继续下一个话题
So let's go on to the next topic.
所以就是这些事件
So events.
我早些时候谈到了这一点
So I spoke of this earlier.
事件只是一种很好的方式 可以说
Events are just a nice way to sort of say when something
如果发生这种情况 请执行此代码块
happens, do this block of code.
你可以在任何地方做到这一点
And you can do this anywhere.
你可以把它从两个不同的物体中分离出来
And you can decouple it from like maybe two different objects
彼此互动
interact with each other.
但您不希望它们传递引用
But you don't want them to sort of pass references
在彼此之间来回移动 并膨胀您的代码
back and forth between each other, and bloat your code.
也许您希望该检查的代码发生在您的主循环中
Maybe you want the code for that check to happen not inside your main loop.
你想把它抽象成某种其他函数
You want to sort of abstract it out to some sort of other function,
就像实例化的事件
like instantiated events.
然后让您的主呈现和更新逻辑
And then have your main rendering and update logic
摆脱所有这些有条件的东西
be free of all this conditional stuff.
所以你创造了事件
So you create event.
你说在一些活动上 所以可能就像在运动员竞走上
You say on some event, so maybe like on player walk,
然后你只需要更新一些 也许是一个标签
and then you just update some, maybe a label
在屏幕的右上角 这给出了玩家的XY
on the top right of the screen, that gives the player's xy.
你就说XY等于那个玩家的XY
And you just say that xy is equal to that player's xy.
我的意思是 除了你可以从字面上
I mean, aside from the fact that you could just literally
画出玩家的XY
draw the player's xy.
但这是相同的原则
But it's the same principle.
您可以在独立于另一个实体的某个位置更新一些值
You can update some value somewhere separate from another entity.
然后等待一个事件 任意定义的事件
And then just wait for an event, arbitrarily defined event,
然后你再播出
that you then broadcast later.
比方说我想要一把广播摇摆剑
So let's say I want a broadcast swing sword.
我有一场挥杆剑比赛
I have a swing sword event.
因此 每当玩家按空格键时 不仅
So whenever the player presses space, not only
他们做了我们之前看到的所有代码 但他们挥舞着剑
do they do all the code that we saw before, but they swing sword.
然后我们说 当你挥舞剑时 传递他们挥舞的地方的XY
And then we say when you swing sword, pass in the xy of wherever they swung
那把剑
the sword.
然后你就可以说好了 在摇摆剑上 看看所有的实体
And so then you can say OK, on swing sword, look at all the entities,
看看XY上的Hitbox是否与它们相撞
and see whether or not the hitbox at xy collides with them.
你可以从以前的逻辑中提取出来 然后把它
And you can sort of take out the logic from where you had it before, and put
把它放在其他集中的地方
it in some other centralized location.
如果你想的话
If you want to.
这种模式更具代表性的是成就系统的理念
More representative of this model is the idea of an achievement system,
而不是每一帧 你可以
where instead of every frame, and you can
有--游戏有许多令人难以置信的成就
have-- games have a ridiculous number of achievements.
有些游戏有1000个这样的成绩
Some games have like 1,000 achievements.
你不会想让这1000个人中的每一个
You don't want to put the test for every one of those 1,000
成就必然在你的更新逻辑之内 对吗？
achievements necessarily inside of your update logic, right?
相反 您可以只为所有人广播一项活动
You can instead just broadcast an event for all
影响这些成就能否实现的不同因素
of the different things that influence whether those achievements are met.
因此 无论一个玩家在一场比赛中需要杀死100个 还是需要100个硬币
So whether a player needs to get 100 kills in a game, or 100 coins.
他们是否需要从悬崖上跳下来
Whether they need to jump off some ledge.
你只是有一些事件来模拟所有这些互动
You just have events that model all these interactions.
活动开始 拿起硬币 做这件事
Event on, pick-up coin, do this.
增加一些时间 一些存储在其他地方的计数器
Increment some time, some counter that's stored somewhere else.
Event.On 杀死生物
Event.on, kill creature.
或者每次你杀生物的时候
Or kill creature triggers every time you,
从字面上讲 一个生物从虚假到死亡都是真实的
literally a creature is sent from as false to dead as true.
也许每当玩家跳跃时 你就会做一个跳跃功能
Maybe whenever the player jumps, you do an on jump function.
然后你可以测试一下--在这段代码中
And then you can test to see whether or not-- in that code,
你可以测试一下他们是否从悬崖上跳了下来
you can test to see whether they jumped off that ledge.
如果发生这种情况 你就有了你的成就系统
And then if that happens, you have your achievement system,
但您并没有所有这些if语句
but you don't have all these if statements,
所有这些测试都发生在你的强制游戏循环中
and all these tests happening inside your sort of imperative game loop.
您只需伪异步地检查所有它们
You can just pseudo asynchronously check for all of them,
在你的游戏中有一个足够详细的事件系统
given a sufficiently detailed event system in your game.
因此 我们将使用的库只是为了展示一点
And so the library that we'll use just to show this a little bit
在刀库里 我们之前用计时器见过
is in the knife library, that we saw before with timer.
Timer.On、Timer.Every、Timer.Tweet
Timer.on, timer.every, timer.tween.
在刀库中 有一个子模块
In the knife library, there's a submodule
名为Event 它允许您调用Event.on
called Event, which allows you to call event.on.
给它一个名称和一个函数
Give it a name and a function.
所以在运动员跳跃上 在运动员跳跃下
So on player jump, off player jump.
你知道?
You know?
功能
Function.
如果Player.Position位于某个悬崖边 或某个相关的区域
If Player.Position is by some cliff, or some area that's relevant,
然后调用这段代码
then call this block of code.
并递增 或将成就设置为真
And increment, or set the achievement to true.
事件 快递
Event.dispatch.
当有事情发生时调度事件
Dispatch an event when something happens.
因此 如果玩家跳跃 那么当他们按空格键时 事件 调度跳跃
So if a player jumps, so when they press the spacebar, event.Dispatch jump.
然后就是您的回调函数需要的任何值
And then just whatever values that your callback function needs.
假设您想要查看悬崖上有什么
Let's say you want to check to see what is on the cliff.
嗯 如果你想看看他们是不是跳下
Well, if you want to check to see whether they jump off
那个特定的悬崖 你需要检查他们的XY位置 想必
that specific cliff, you need to check their xy position, presumably,
因此 只需通过Event.Dispatch传递可选参数即可
so you can just pass in optional parameters via event.dispatch.
你可以说OK 调度运动员跳跃的事件
You can say OK, dispatch the event that the player jumped,
然后说这名球员跳到了XY
and say that the player jumped at xy.
所以这个函数回调将访问xy
And so this function call back is going to have access to the xy.
它会说好的 一跳 我说我得到了
It's going to say OK, on jump, I say I got,
我的回调是由player.x player.y调用的 它碰巧--
I'm getting my callback called with player.x player.Y. And it happens to--
哦 它不在悬崖上
oh, it's not at the cliff.
所以什么都没发生
So nothing happens.
或者是悬崖 所以成就 跳下悬崖 解锁才是真的
Or it is the cliff, so the achievement, jump off cliff, unlocked is true.
现在的测试并不是每一帧都在进行
And test now is not happening every single frame,
否则就有可能
which otherwise would potentially.
而且它不会阻止你的更新逻辑为您的球员跳跃
And it's not blocking up your update logic for your player jumping.
对吧？
Right?
播放器 播放器内的跳转逻辑 播放器跳转状态
The player, the jumping logic inside player, the player jumps state,
不需要知道
doesn't need to know--
不需要问我们是不是从悬崖上跳下去了
doesn't need to ask whether or not we've jumped off a cliff.
我们应该把它写进成就档案里
That's something that we should just delegate to our achievement file,
或者随便你怎么说
or whatever you want.
这就是事件给你的灵活性
And that's sort of the flexibility that events afford you.
所以我们使用事件
So we use event.
我会在这里简单地讲一下
I'll touch on this a little bit briefly here.
但基本上 如果我们在第21.39行进入参与人步行状态
But basically, if we go to the player walk state on line 21.39, first of all
我们在检查输入
we're checking for input here.
对吧？
Right?
我们只是说如果我们按左 右 上 下
We're just saying if we press the left, right, up, or down.
方向是向左走 向右走 等等
The direction is that walk left, walk right, so on and so forth.
然后我们调用实体walk state. update
And then what we do is we call entity walk state.update.
所以这个存在于实体中的基本状态代码 这样我们就可以
So this base walk state code that exists in entity, so that we can
让每个实体都有这个代码
let every single entity have this code.
它所做的只是检查
All it does just check to see whether or not
它所属的玩家或实体撞墙
the player or entity that it belongs to hit a wall.
如果是这样 那么set there bumped等于true
And if it did, then set there bumped equals true.
它所做的只是一面旗帜 上面写着 好吧 玩家撞到了一堵墙
And what it does is just a flag that says, OK, the player bumped a wall.
好吗？
OK?
这有什么关系
Why is that relevant?
因为在我们打完电话之后 我们可以说 好吧 如果我们撞到了一堵墙
Because then, after we call that, we can say, OK, if we bumped a wall,
并且这仅在玩家处于行走状态时发生
and this only happens when the player walk state,
如果我们在看左边 暂时调整一下我们的位置
if we're looking to the left, temporarily adjust our position.
因为当它撞到你的时候 它会把你打回原来的世界
Because when it bumps you, it knocks you back out back into the world.
但我们要重新调整位置到我们相撞的地方
But we're going to re-bump our position into wherever we collided.
我们要检查每一个入口 然后
We're going to look at every doorway, and then
假设我们撞上了门 门开着
we're going to say if we collided with that doorway, and it's open,
然后我们把它移到门口的中央
then we're going to shift it to the center of the doorway
这样看起来就不会像玩家在穿墙而过
so that it doesn't look as if the player is walking through the wall.
我们要把它设置到墙所在的地方
We're going to set it to wherever the wall is,
或者门在哪里 门口的正中央
or wherever the door is, the very center of the doorway.
然后我们要召集行动调度班
And then we're going to call event.Dispatch shift,
朝那个方向
and in that direction.
所以左移 右移 上移 下移
So shift left, shift right, shift up, and shift down.
所以这四个不同的例子都会说好的
And so all of these four different cases are going to say OK,
玩家撞到了一个门
the player has hit a doorway.
我在某个地方有一个功能
I have a function somewhere.
事件 打开 向下移动 向左移动 向右移动 向上移动
Event.on, shift down, shift left, shift right, shift up.
会触发什么？
That's going to trigger what?
隔壁房间
The next room.
它会触发我们移动到下一个房间 也是下一个房间
It's going to trigger us moving to the next room, and also the next room
产卵 摄像机也在移动位置
spawning, and the camera sort of shifting position.
密码在地牢里
So the code for this is in dungeon.
所以我们继续看地牢
So we're going to go ahead and look at dungeon.
所以就在这里 第29到43行 事件
So right here, on line 29 through 43, event.on,
左移 右移 上移 下移
shift left, shift right, shift up, shift down.
它所做的是我们有另一个函数 叫做开始转移
And what that does is we have another function called begin shifting,
它接受x和y
which takes in an x and y.
负虚拟宽度 虚拟宽度 负虚拟高度
Negative virtual width, virtual width, negative virtual height,
虚拟高度
virtual height.
有人记得为什么要把这些数字传进去吗？
Does anybody recall why we need to pass those numbers in there?
如果我们向左移动 传递一个负的虚拟宽度
If we're shifting left, and we're passing a negative virtual width,
你觉得会是多少
what do you think that number is going to be?
记住每个房间都有相邻的偏移量x和y
So recall every room has an adjacent offset x and y
它渲染了这个房间 基本上添加了偏移量
that renders that room with that offset basically added to it.
它的x和y
Its x and y.
如果我们开始向左移动
So if we begin shifting to the left, negative virtual width
就是x偏移量
is going to be the x offset.
因为那个房间需要向左渲染一个屏幕宽度 对吗？
Because that room needs to be rendered a screen width to the left, right?
以此类推 以获得正确的虚拟宽度
And so on for the right, virtual width.
它将虚拟宽度添加到x偏移
It adds a virtual width to the x offset.
相邻的x偏移
The adjacent x offset.
然后是虚拟高度 负数和正数表示上移和下移
And then virtual height, negative and positive for shift up, and shift down.
所以开始切换 基本上这是一个补间操作
So begin shifting, basically the gist of this is it's a tween operation.
所以我们从这里开始 调用timer.tween 只需要取一个值并插值
So we start here, recall timer.tween, just takes a value and interpolates it.
self 我们有一个摄像机和一个摄像机y 对吧？
So self, we have a camera and a camera y, right?
等于x和y的位移
Going to equal shift x and shift y.
最终会的
Eventually.
所以移位x和移位y是相邻的偏移量 所以我们
So shift x and shift y being the adjacent offset, that we're
需要把相机移开
going to need to shift the camera by.
所以X相机和Y相机 它们都是零 总是
So camera x and camera y, they both sort of zero, always.
当房间完全完工的时候
When the room gets completely finalized.
所以如果移位x是虚拟宽度 负虚拟宽度
So if the shift x is virtual width, negative virtual width,
因为我们在向左移动 然后它就会
cause we're shifting left, then it's going
让摄像机在一秒钟内从右向左移动 对吗？
to tween the camera going from right to left over the span of a second, right?
然后玩家 玩家x和玩家y
And then the player, the player x and player y,
这些基本上都是在这里设置在另一端
those are basically set up here to the opposite end
房间的另一个房间
of the room, the next room.
因此 如果玩家从房间的顶端出发
So if the player is going from the top of the room
到隔壁房间的底部 它需要得到它的x和y
to the bottom of the next room, it needs to get its x and y
放在那个位置 隔壁房间的底部
put in that position, the bottom part of the next room.
或者隔壁房间的左边部分 如果它们是从右边移动的 对吗？
Or the left part of the next room, if they're moving from the right, right?
或者它们的右边部分是从左边移动的
Or the right part of they're moving from the left.
最下面的部分 如果他们向上移动的话
And the bottom part if they're moving up.
如果他们向下移动 则是向上的部分
And the up part if they're moving down.
所以这就是所有的作用
So that's all that does.
把他们放在正确的位置 在隔壁房间
Puts them in the right position, on the next room.
他们两个人 摄像机和播放器
Tweens both of them, the camera and the player,
因为球员需要不停地移动到隔壁房间
because the player needs to keep moving to the next room.
而且相机需要向上移动
And the camera needs to shift up.
当它完成时 我们称其为完成移位
When it's finished, we call finished shifting,
这只是一个函数 基本上所有的东西都是0
which is just a function that says basically everything to 0.
它将当前房间设置为下一个房间
It sets the current room to the next room.
它将摄像机x和所有这些东西都设置为0
It sets the camera x and all that stuff all to 0,
然后所有实体和对象都设置为0
and then all the entities and objects there, it all gets set to 0.
因此 它们的偏移量为0
So they are offset to 0.
所以一切基本上都是正确的 在0.0
So that everything is basically right at 0.0
再一次 就像一开始一样
again, just like it was at the very beginning.
最后但同样重要的是 当我们进入新房间时
And then last but not least, when we get into the new room,
我们一开始就把所有的门都打开
we start with the doors all open.
然后当我们走进这里的房间时 因为这就是
And then when we get into the room here, because this is all
在完成的函数中完成 调用 这
done in the finished function, recall, this
只有在补间结束后才会发生
will only happen after the tween is completed.
每个入口都将被设置为False
Every doorway is going to get set to false.
打开等于假
Open equals false.
所以我们一进隔壁房间所有的门都会关上
So all the doors will close as soon as we get into the next room,
在我们做完补丁手术之后
after we've performed the tween operation.
然后我们将播放一段门声
And then we'll play a door sound.
这就是实际执行移位操作所涉及的代码
So that's the code involved in actually doing the shift operation.
所以我们能够触发它
So we were able to trigger it.
我们不一定要在玩家漫游状态下执行该代码
We don't have to necessarily do that code from the player walk state.
我们只是说 如果球员撞到门口
We just say if the players collide with the doorway,
然后调度一个由地牢处理的事件
then dispatch an event that is handled by dungeon.
因为地牢有权进入现在的房间 隔壁的房间 以及所有的东西
Because dungeon has access to current room, next room, and all the stuff
它需要真正地进行这种转变
that it needs to actually perform that transition.
所以我们有两个分离的 但它们工作得很好
So we have the two that are sort of decoupled but they work well
彼此齐头并进
in tandem with one another.
那么 有谁对这是如何运作的有疑问吗？
So anybody have questions as to sort of how this works?
好的
OK.
这基本上就是地下城的滚动
That's essentially the dungeon scrolling.
这是一次青少年行动
It's a tween operation.
这是一个摄像头 一个临时的房间被渲染
It's a camera, a temporary room gets rendered.
我们搬到一个临时房间 一切都恢复到0
We move to a temporary room, everything gets set back to 0.
然后 这实际上就是那种行为的疯狂循环
And then it's just a wild loop of that sort of behavior, effectively.
我们使用事件库在某种程度上清理了整个方面
And we use the event library to sort of clean up that whole aspect.
屏幕在这里滚动 这是另一个演示
And sort of screen scrolling here, just another demonstration.
我们详细地看过了 但这是一个很好的GIF
We went over it in detail, but this is a nice GIF
我发现这在某种程度上概括了这意味着什么
I found that sort of encapsulates what that means.
模版是我们之前看到的东西
Stenciling is something that we saw earlier.
如果我们把它看作一张模板 那么我们
And if we look at this as a stencil, so we
可以假装这些是心脏的圆圈
can pretend that these are the circle of the heart,
而那个长方形是一张模板
and that rectangle are a stencil.
然后我们想在这些模板上画一个灰色的矩形
And then we want to draw this gray rectangle on top of those stencils.
我们可以使用模板来遮盖特定的部分 这
We can use the stencil to mask out specific parts, which
否则很难做到这一点
would otherwise be pretty tough to do.
我是说 很难有必要 也许是个别
I mean, it's hard to necessarily, maybe individually
渲染像素 或创建类似如下的形状
render pixels, or create a shape that sort of looks like this.
对于许多非常有趣的视觉效果来说要容易得多
Much easier for a lot of very interesting visual effects
使用任意形状和大小的模板
to use a stencil of arbitrary shape and size.
你也可以使用图像
And you can use images, too.
你可以使用模具的图像 来创造一些非常酷的效果
You can use images of stencils, to create some pretty cool effects.
我们以前讨论过它 当我谈到拱门的时候
We went over it before, when I talked about the archway.
所以我不会过多地详述
So I won't go over into much more detail.
但是 你可以再一次看到 它到底在哪里？
But again, you can look at that in the, where was it exactly?
它在房间的功能里 房间里 对不起
It was in the room function, room class, sorry.
就在这下面的底部
Down here at the bottom.
所以从213行到229行 记住它们是模板函数
So lines to 213 to 229 recall they're a stencil function.
这两个函数尤其是您需要使用的
The couple functions in particular that you need to use
是love.graph 绘制模板的模板 然后
are love.graphics.stencil which draws the stencils, and then
Love.graph ics.setstenciltest 比较
love.graphics.setstenciltest which compares
模板将值设置为某个值 并绘制它们
the stencil values to some value, and draws them
无论该条件是否为真
whether or not that condition is true.
所以我们在这里有我们的函数 画四个矩形
So we have our function here, which draws four rectangles.
这些都是拱门
Those are all the archways.
它将绘制到这些矩形的所有像素替换为值1
It replaces any pixels that get drawn to those rectangles with the value 1.
模板值为1 因此模板值为
The stencil value 1, so stencil value is just
类似于一个隐藏值 它确定图像是否将
like a hidden value that determines whether a image will get
不管它是不是被模压过的
drawn if it's being stenciled or not.
设定模板测试意味着我们正在寻找小于1的任何值
Set stencil test means that we're looking for anything less than 1.
我们会画出来的
And we'll draw that.
因为玩家将会是1 如果它是
And because the player is going to be 1 if it's
在任何这些模板矩形上 它都不会
on any of those stencil rectangles, it will not
如果球员与这些模板矩形重叠 请绘制该球员
draw the player if it overlaps with those stencil rectangles.
这就是它通常的工作原理
And so that's in general how it works.
你可以这样做 有很多不同的比较
And you can do, there's a lot different comparisons.
您可以执行大于1的操作
You can do greater than 1.
你可以做迭代模版 这样你就可以增加价值
You can do iterative stenciling so that you can increment of value.
您可以使用介于0和255之间的简单值
You can have simple values go between 0 and 255.
有很多有趣的效果 你可以用它
There's a lot of interesting effects you can get with that.
但我们刚才看到的一般用法是将值设置为1
But the general use that we just saw is set the values to one,
如果要绘制它们 请检查它们是否小于1
and check to see whether they're less than 1, if you want to draw them.
如果你不想画它们的话
If you want to not draw them.
有没有人对模版制作有疑问
Does anybody have questions how stenciling works,
以及这些功能是如何工作的？
and how these functions work?
嗯?
Yeah?
观众：所以就像用Stat模具把门遮住一样？
AUDIENCE: So like having stat stencil cover up the door?
所以当你画玩家的时候 你不会真的
So when you draw the player, you won't actually
在模板上画 [INAUDIBLE]
draw on the stencil, [INAUDIBLE].
科尔顿·奥格登：是的
COLTON OGDEN: Yes.
所以这就像是让模板矩形越过门口
So it's like having the stencil rectangles go over the doorway,
这样当球在他们下面时 球员就不会被抽到
so that the player will not get drawn when it's underneath them.
如果我回到有它的幻灯片上
If I go back to a slide that has it.
模板在这里
The stencils are here.
对吗？
Right?
我必须通过并弄清楚我需要的确切的XY
I had to go through and figure out the exact xy that I needed for them.
而且还有一个--
And there is a--
您可以做的是 您可以将模板函数
what you can do is you can take that stencil function that
画出矩形 然后你就可以把它从模具测试中拿出来
draws the rectangles, and you can just take it out of the stencil test,
然后你看
and see.
实际上 您将能够看到确切的矩形在哪里
You will actually be able to see where the exact rectangles are.
因为那样它就会直接画出长方形
Because then it will just literally draw the rectangles.
但在这里 基本上就在这里和隔壁房间的位置之间
But here, basically right between here and where it would be on the next room.
所以当我们从这里走到隔壁房间时 它仍然是
So that when we go from here over into the next room, it's still
用模板来刻印它们
stencils them.
就在这里 球员要检查他们
Right here, the player is going to go over them.
它会将其模板值设置为1
It's going to set its stencil value to 1.
它正在检查要呈现的任何小于1的值
It's checking for anything less than 1 to render.
所以它不会通过测试 它会
So it's going to fail the test, and it's going
在这一点上不会抽到那个球员
to not draw that player at that point.
因此 它实际上只是掩盖了玩家
So it's effectively just masking out the player,
因为我们给它分配了正确的模板值
because we're assigning it to the right stencil value,
我们对此进行了正确的比较
and we're doing the right comparison for it.
但是 是的 实际上就是这样
But yeah, that's effectively it.
只是用它来 因为我们处于一种情况
Just using it to, because we were in a situation
我们的瓷砖不能干净利落地画出来
where our tiles didn't cleanly lend themselves to drawing over
球员 你可以做到的
the player, which you could do.
你可以在拱门下面画阴影部分
You could draw the shadow part underneath the archway part,
然后只需更改渲染顺序
and then just change the rendering order.
但我们拥有的电子表格并没有为我们提供这种灵活性
But the spreadsheet that we had didn't afford us that flexibility.
因此 我们采用了更有趣的模版方法
So we went with a little more interesting stenciling approach
为完成任务干杯
to getting it done.
我们之前看过这个
We looked at this earlier.
所以游戏设计靠的是数据 而不是一堆逻辑
So game design via data, rather than a bunch of logic.
所以你越能在游戏中对你的任何东西进行建模
So the more you can sort of get towards modeling your anything in your game
像这样的数据 你的引擎越灵活
like data, like this, the more flexible your engine is,
人们就越容易修改你的游戏
the easier it is for people to mod your game.
这一点非常重要
Which is hugely important.
你越容易让设计师
And the easier it is for you to let designers
负责为你的游戏创造资产
take charge of actually creating assets for your game.
所以这里我们创建了一个任意的数据集合
So here we've created an arbitrary collection of data,
你可以想怎么复杂就怎么复杂
and you can get as complex with this as you want to.
唯一真正重要的是你的游戏引擎
The only thing that really matters is whether your game engine
支持这些字段 并相应地对这些字段进行操作
supports those fields, and acts on those fields accordingly.
但一旦发生 我是说
But once it does, I mean, the more things
你就越有可能添加新的东西
you add, the more possibilities you have for adding new things.
所以地精 我们有健康 力量
So goblin, we have health, strength.
因此 我们的游戏引擎应该考虑到强度
So strength should be accounted for in our game engine.
这是 我们现在谈论的只是一般的抽象意义
And this is, we're talking in just the general abstract sense now.
比如说我们在做一个RPG什么的
Let's say we're like making an RPG or something.
或许这是我们塞尔达游戏的一部分
Or maybe this is part of our Zelda game.
如果我们再详细一点
If we got a little bit more detailed with it.
但是地精将是一个有10点生命的生物
But goblin is going to be a creature that has 10 health.
它有两个强度 所以这些值
It's got two strength, so these values will
当它被创建为一个实体时被加载
get loaded when it's created as an entity,
力量是我们的引擎
and strength is some value that our engine
需要适用于它决定攻击的任何东西
needs to apply to anything that it decides to attack.
对吧？
Right?
你可以在防守上做同样的事情
You could do the same thing with defense.
你可以创造任意的东西
You could create arbitrary things.
有妖精的质感
It's got a goblin texture.
这就是雪碧
So that's the sprite.
我们在这里定义了一些动画
We've defined some animations here, which
你已经看到了如何在我们的游戏引擎中实例化它们
you've already seen how to instantiate those in our game engine.
可能是从棍棒开始的
Maybe it starts off with a club weapon.
你也可以参考其他类型的Lua文件
And you can also reference other sort of Lua files
如果你有武器定义文件的话
that have these definitions, if you have maybe a weapons defs file.
你可以索引到武器defs俱乐部 然后那个俱乐部项目
You could index into weapons defs club, and then that club item
也许会有一些自己的特点
will maybe have a bunch of its own characteristics
当你的游戏引擎加载这个地精def时
that when your game engine is loading this goblin def,
它也会加载club def 并实例化一堆特性
it loads in the club def as well, and instantiates a bunch of qualities
到那个实体上 或者那个项目上
onto that entity, or that item, that then have
与游戏引擎相关的行为
behavior relevant to your game engine.
侵略性是真的
Aggressive is true.
所以如果某个东西是实体的 侵略性的 那么它可能就是人工智能
So if something is entity.Aggressive, then maybe it's AI
会去找玩家
will seek out the player.
对吧？
Right?
您可以将其设置为False
And you can set it to false.
所以现在你可以区分追逐玩家的实体
So now you can differentiate between entities that chase the player,
和一些温顺的实体 只是做他们自己随机的事情
and entities that are sort of docile, and just do their own random thing.
晚上睡觉
Sleeps at night.
也许你的游戏有一个昼夜循环
Maybe your game has a day/night cycle.
也许有些实体保持清醒 有些进入睡眠状态 对吗？
Maybe some entities stay awake, and some go into a sleep state, right?
所以它看起来会说好的 现在是晚上
So it will look and say OK, it's nighttime,
这个实体在晚上睡觉吗？
does the entity sleep at night?
如果是这样的话 没问题
If it does, OK.
然后实体改变状态 休眠 对吗？
Then entity change state, sleep, right?
然后在白天 当白天发生的时候
And then during the day, when the day happens,
您将以相反的方式做同样的事情
you'll do the same thing in reverse.
你会说如果实体在晚上睡觉
You'll say if the entity sleeps at night,
然后你说实体 觉醒是真的
then you say entity.awake is true.
或者什么都行
Or whatever it is.
将状态更改为清醒、空闲或行走
Change state awake, or idle, or walking.
然后是易燃物
And then flammable.
也许你有武器可以造成伤害 或者开火
Maybe you have weapons that shoot damage, or shoot fire.
或者你有可以发射火焰的手电筒 或者一些--
Or maybe you have torches that shoot fire, or some--
也许你处在像熔岩一样的水平
maybe you're in a level that's like lava.
你知道 如果你触摸其中一块瓷砖 它就会产生易燃效果
And you know, if you touch one of the tiles, it has a flammable effect.
如果它是易燃的 可能你的状态也是易燃的
And if it's flammable, may be your status equals flammable.
随着时间的推移 你会受到伤害
You take damage over time.
然后你改变你的动画
And you change your animation.
也许你会被染成红色 或者类似的颜色
Maybe you'd get tinted red, or something like that.
但考虑到所有这些不同的可能性
But thinking about all these different possibilities,
就像你的引擎所能做的一样 你几乎可以任意地创造
like what your engine is capable of, you can create pretty much arbitrarily
复杂的数据结构和实体 以及项
complex data structures and entities, and items,
和你想要的任何东西 而不是
and whatever you want in your game, without having
来创建一个妖精职业
to create a goblin class.
或者是一个骨架类
Or a skeleton class.
或者是一个任意复杂的生物类别
Or a arbitrarily complex creature class.
你只需要用属性和模型组合你的生物
You just compose your creature with attributes and model
它的行为就是这样的
its behavior that way.
组成重于继承 我们上周谈到了
Composition over inheritance, which we talked about last week,
在游戏设计中非常有价值
is very valuable in game design.
这就是Unity的游戏引擎所采用的方法
And that's what Unity's game engine sort of approaches.
由于实体是纯实体组件系统
Because entity is a purely entity component system,
其中实体被建模为组件的集合
whereby entities are modeled as collections of components
每个人都做了一些事情
that each do something.
我们也几乎可以把它们看作是组件
And we can sort of almost think of these as components, too.
尽管是在一种简单得多的表现形式中
Albeit in a much simpler sort of representation.
有没有人对此有疑问 或者为什么它有用
Does anybody have questions of this, or like why it's useful,
或诸如此类的事？
or anything like that?
好的
OK.
所以我今天最不想谈的就是 我看到了一两个学生
So the last thing I wanted to talk about today, and I saw one or two students
提到他们多么希望自己知道 或者多么希望我们
were mentioning how they wished they knew, or wish we
更多地谈了一下当时是如何进行编程的
talked about a little bit more how programming was done back in the day.
所以我不一定是6502汇编编程方面的专家
So I'm not an expert, necessarily, in programming 6502 assembly,
这就是NES是用来写的
which is what the NES is written in.
有很多人在这方面做得很好
There are a lot of people that are very good at it.
但这里有一些联系
But there's a few links here.
所以在幻灯片中 如果你想看网站上的幻灯片
So in the slides, if you wanted to look at the slides on the website,
实际上 自制酒在某些社区中相当受欢迎
Homebrew is actually quite a popular thing amongst certain communities
上网
online.
以及它本质上为编译器带来了什么
And what it is essentially getting compilers
这将为某些任意处理器或开发编译源代码
that will compile source code for some arbitrary processor, or development
来自某个任意计算机系统的环境
environment from some arbitrary computer system.
像NES一样 它是一台基于8位微处理器的机器
Like the NES, which was a 8-bit microprocessor based machine
拥有自己的一套有趣的硬件
with its own set of interesting hardware.
它允许您为此编译程序集
It allowed you to compile the assembly for that
并通过一个名为模拟器的程序实际运行它
and actually run it via a program called an emulator.
而仿真器只允许您运行ROM映像 或者只运行任意数据
And an emulator just allows you to run ROM images, or just arbitrary data
它映射到某个系统的机器指令
that maps to the machine instructions of some system
仿真器已经通过虚拟机进行了仿真
that the emulator has emulated via virtual machine.
因此 如果你想更详细地研究它
And so if you wanted to look into it a little bit more in detail,
这里有几个链接
there's a couple of links here.
所以 NES.wiki有很多很棒的链接
So NES.wiki has got a bunch of great links.
有一本编程指南是这样写的
There's a Programming Guide that kind of goes
关于如何进行一些6502组装以及如何使用NES的基础知识
over the basics of how to do some 6502 assembly as well as with the NES,
以及它的特殊硬件
and its particular hardware.
然后大多数人使用的编译器被称为CC 65
And then the compiler that most people use for this is called CC 65,
它是一个65 02汇编语言编译器
which is a 65 02 assembly compiler.
这是一些源代码的一个例子
And so this is an example of some source code.
这本书读起来有点难
It's a little bit tough to read.
但我不能放大 我想不是
But I can't zoom in, I don't think.
但大意是你有很多--
But the gist of it is you have a lot of--
在这里 实际上我可以在网上调出它
and here, actually I could pull it up online.
让我试试看
Le me try.
超级马里奥反汇编
Super Mario disassembly.
那就去这里吧
So go here.
这是在Github上
This is on Github.
所以有人反编译 基本上 或者说反汇编
So somebody decompiled, basically, or disassembled rather,
获取代表Super的所有机器代码和ROM镜像的字节
took the bytes that represent all the machine code and the ROM image of Super
Mario Bros 然后将其转换回汇编语言
Mario Bros and then just converted it back to assembly language,
然后给它添加了评论
and then added comments to it.
因为我不会太详细地讲什么是组装
Because I won't go into too much detail about what assembly is,
以及它是如何工作的 但本质上说 它只是
and how it works, but essentially it's just
直接位于机器代码上方的一层 其中关键字
a layer directly above machine code where the keywords
映射到内存中的基本字节数
map to essentially what are bytes in memory
它们实际上是程序指令
that are actually program instructions.
这会影响你的CPU的行为 这样你就可以得到程序
And that influence the behavior of your CPU such that you get programs.
而这就是c语言的基础 在它的每一种语言中
And that's what c is layered on top of, an in every language thereof,
之后
thereafter.
所以如果我放大这里 看看我能不能
So if I zoom in here, see if I can.
它有点慢了
It's being a little slow.
但它让我--
But it's letting me--
所以我们可以在这里看到
so here we can see.
我认为它滞后是因为文件太大了
I think it's lagging because the file is just so large.
这就像是14000行代码
It's like 14,000 lines of code.
因为组装是一件很长很长的事情
Because the thing about assembly is assembly is a very, very long.
因为有太多的--
Because there are so many--
你需要有 就像真的很慢
you need to have, just like really slowly.
无限放大
Zooming in infinitely.
你需要做的步骤太多了
There are just so many steps you need to do in order
为了实现像C这样的高级语言所实现的相同功能
to achieve the same thing that you get in a high level language like C,
甚至比这更高的语言
or even languages higher than that.
认为很多事情都是理所当然的 特别是像加载这样的事情
Taking a lot of things for granted, especially things like loading
寄存器
registers.
所以每个CPU都有一系列可以存储数值的寄存器
So every CPU has got a series of registers that can store values,
然后CPU有逻辑 你基本上可以
and then the CPU has logic that you can basically
说OK 如果寄存器A中的值大于或等于某个值
say OK, if the value in register a is greater than or equal to some value,
然后转移到汇编代码的这个序列
then branch to this sequence of the assembly code.
通常 您必须在字节级执行和/或操作
And often you'll have to do things like and/or operations on byte level,
仅以字节为单位
just on bytes.
就像这里 我们可以看到我们正在结束值3
Like right here, we can see we're ending the value 3 on whatever
在登记簿a中
is in register a.
就像我说的 不要太过沉迷于什么是组装
Like I said, don't intend to get too much into what assembly is.
但对于那些好奇游戏是如何在80年代实现的 甚至
But for those curious as to how games were implemented in the '80s, and even
90年代早期 都是用汇编语言
the early '90s, it was all in assembly language.
因为汇编语言就是你
Because assembly language is you're literally
对你要编程的机器的CPU进行编程
programming the CPU of whatever machine you're trying to program.
这就是你如何获得尽可能多的效率
And that's how you get as much efficiency as possible.
如果你了解你的计算环境 你就知道你的CPU能做什么
If you know your computing, environment you know what your CPU is capable of.
关于编译像C C++ 或Java这样的语言
The thing about compiling a language like C, or C++, or Java,
这是一个比那些更高的抽象
which is even higher of an abstraction than those,
就是你允许某种算法为你做这些工作
is you're allowing sort of algorithms to do the work for you.
你允许算法把你的源代码
You're allowing algorithms to take your source code
然后把它变成这样
and turn it into this, basically.
比这层低一层 有效
A layer lower than this, effectively.
这是它所产生的一个中间层次
This is an intermediary level that it does generate.
但可以说 在80年代和90年代
But suffice to say, in the '80s and '90s,
C编译器在创建游戏方面不如人类
C compilers were not as good as humans were in creating games,
特别是做很多他们需要做的棘手的事情
especially to do a lot of the tricky things that they needed to do,
为了让它们在处理器上高效地工作 在当时
in order to get them working efficiently on processors that were, at the time,
1到3兆赫的速度
one to three megahertz in speed.
现在我们有三个千兆赫的处理器 这没什么大不了的
Which now we have like three gigahertz processors, and it's no big deal.
但这实际上是一个窗口
But that is effectively, that's sort of a window
80年代和90年代开发游戏的情况
into what it was like developing games in the '80s and '90s.
然后在90年代 像N64 Playstation 1这样的东西
And then in the '90s, with like things like N64 Playstation 1,
在Playstation 2上 等等 它通常是用一种语言完成的
going onto Playstation 2, and so forth, it was typically done in a language
比如C或C++
like C or C++.
有时候有一些变种
Sometimes with some variants.
某些游戏机 如PS3有一个臭名昭著的困难的图形
Certain consoles, like the PS3 has a notoriously difficult graphics
处理器编程
processor to program.
所以很多PS3的三个团队需要在汇编中编程
So a lot of PS3 three teams needed to program in assembly,
即使是在2007年 2009年
even at the time, which was 2007, 2009.
但这就是 简而言之 它就像编程的65 02
But that's, in a nutshell, what it's like programming the 65 02.
如果你想看上面的链接
So if you want, those links up above, it's
一个很有启发性的经历
a pretty enlightening experience actually digging
并试图理解大会的工作
into that sort of thing, and trying to make sense of what the assembly does.
这很困难 也很繁重 因为
It's quite difficult, and quite burdensome because of how long
这些程序是什么 每个指令是多么的微小
these programs are, and just how minute each individual instruction is.
就像只是检查 只是把一个值加载到一个寄存器
Like just checking, just loading a value into a register,
循环通常只是迭代地加载一个值
just to do a loop often will just be iteratively loading a value
到一个寄存器
into a register.
然后像执行一些操作 或计算 从那里
And then like performing some operation, or calculation, off of that.
然后分支到其他代码循环
And then branching to some other loop of code.
很多内容都可以压缩成几行C语言
A lot of that can be condensed into like just a couple of lines of C,
或者更少的Lua行
or even fewer lines of Lua.
所以更多的负担 但有洞察力
So a lot more of a burden but there is insight.
肯定是对深入调查的一些见解
Definitely some insight into digging a little deeper
看向那里
and sort of looking there.
这些都是NES开发wiki上的链接
So once again, those are the links on the NES dev wiki.
Wiki.NESdev.com如果你有兴趣看的话
Wiki.NESdev.com if you're interested in looking at that.
在作业5中 就像你在作业4中做的那样
In Assignment 5, like you did in Assignment 4,
你可以创建一个可消耗的游戏对象
you can create a game object that's consumable.
可以随意使用作业4中的代码来完成此任务
And feel free to use code from Assignment 4 to do this.
当你定义你的消费函数时
When like you define your on consume function,
如果你们打算采用和上次作业相同的模式 那么有什么想法吗
if you're going to adopt the same model as the last assignment, then any ideas
我们该怎么做
as to what we need to do?
可能只是增加了破坏实体的反义词 对吧？
Probably just add the opposite of damage the entity, right?
我们想添加心脏
We want to add hearts.
我们希望将HP添加到其中
We want to add HP to it.
你会看到在发行版中health被建模为偶数
And you'll see in the distro that health is modeled as an even number,
因为每一个数字都是半颗心
because every one digit is half a heart.
是的
Yes.
问：你能给一个负数吗？
AUDIENCE: Can you give a negative number to [INAUDIBLE]??
科尔顿·奥格登：你可以
COLTON OGDEN: You can.
这实际上也是同样的事情
And that will effectively be the same thing, too.
是的
So.
第二部分是包括锅
The second part is including pots.
所以在精灵表中有罐子
So there are pots in the sprite sheet.
所以这些应该是实心的
So these should be solid.
当玩家与他们互动时
So when the player interacts with them, he
应该把他赶出去
should be bumped out of where he was.
让玩家举起它们
Allow the player to lift them.
所以在精灵表中有一个动画 它实际上允许--
So there's an animation in the sprite sheet that will actually allow--
显示玩家举起罐子
that shows the player lifting up the pot.
所以你可能需要一个新的状态 玩家举罐状态
So you probably need a new state, player lift pot state.
与大麻州同行
Walk with pot state.
不管你怎么定义它
Whatever you want to define it as.
但你基本上需要有这两个人 才能让这件事起作用
But you'll need basically to have those two in order to get this to work.
我们需要做的一件事是什么？
What's one thing that we'll need to do in order for the player
抬起锅来
to lift the pot.
有什么主意吗？
Any ideas?
除了渲染方面 例如 当玩家四处走动时
Besides the rendering aspect of it, when the player walks around, for example,
需要采取什么措施？
what needs to happen?
如果他拿着罐子的话
If he's holding the pot.
观众：他比较慢
AUDIENCE: He's slower.
科尔顿·奥格登：你可以让他慢一点
COLTON OGDEN: You can make him slower.
是的 这是有可能的
Yeah, that's possible.
这不是作业所必需的
That's not required for the assignment.
比这更基本的
More fundamental than that.
赌注需要追踪玩家的位置 对吗？
The pot needs to track the player's location, right?
它需要相对于球员的位置
It needs to be relative to the player's location.
因此 保持赌注可能比玩家高出一小部分
So keep the pot probably above the player by some amount.
对于如何实现这一点 我不会太挑剔
I won't be too picky as to how you implement that.
但博彩需要跟踪玩家
But the pot needs to track the player.
实际上 这就是下一点
Which is this next point, actually.
行走的动画 就像我说的 应该
And the walking animations, like I said, should
在他们拿着的时候换衣服
change while they're carrying it.
最后 允许玩家投掷水壶
Allow the player, lastly, to throw the pot.
所以当你扔罐子的时候 基本上就是把罐子变成了抛射物
So when you throw the pot, basically turn the pot into a projectile.
如果它撞到了其中一面墙 就把它打破
If it hits one of the walls, break it.
您可以只是立即取消绘制 或有一些动画
You can either just despawn it instantly, or have some animation.
由你决定
It's up to you.
但是 如果它撞到了墙 就放弃它
But just, if it hits a wall, despawn it.
触发它--可能只是触发它到一些值 假
Trigger it to-- maybe just trigger it to some values, false.
渲染是假的 无论你想做什么
Render is false, whatever you want to do.
如果它击中敌人 它应该会对敌人造成一次伤害
If it hits an enemy, it should damage the enemy by one,
就像我们已经看到的一样
just like we've seen already.
如果它运行的距离超过四块瓷砖
And if it travels farther than four tiles,
除了还撞到其中一堵墙 然后把它也毁了
in addition to also hitting one of the walls, then destroy it too.
这些都是作业5的主要组成部分
So those are the main components for Assignment 5.
而你实现大部分目标的方式是相当灵活的
And the ways that which you achieve most of it's fairly flexible.
但没错 这就是第五课 塞尔达传奇
But yeah, that's Lecture 5, Legend of Zelda.
所以感谢你们的光临
So thanks for coming.
下次见
I'll see you next time.